<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno. XXVIII. Henrici VIII. Actes made in the parliament bego[n]ne and holden at Westm[inster], the. VIII. daye of Iune, in the. XXVIII. yere of the reygne of our most drad soueraine lord kyng Henry the. VIII. and there continued and kepte tyll the dissolution of the same parliament the. XVIII. of Iuly, to the honour of God, and for the common weale and profyt of this realme.</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. 1536-1537. 28 Hen.VIII</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9394.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898994</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898994</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1984:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno. XXVIII. Henrici VIII. Actes made in the parliament bego[n]ne and holden at Westm[inster], the. VIII. daye of Iune, in the. XXVIII. yere of the reygne of our most drad soueraine lord kyng Henry the. VIII. and there continued and kepte tyll the dissolution of the same parliament the. XVIII. of Iuly, to the honour of God, and for the common weale and profyt of this realme.</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. 1536-1537. 28 Hen.VIII</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
                  <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Tho. Berthelet Regis impressor excudebat, cum priuilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Anno vicesimo octavo. Henrici octavi.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, the imprint is in four lines--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁶ D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO. XXVIII. HENRICI VIII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ACTES MADE IN THE parliament bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> at Weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the <hi>.VIII.</hi> daye of Iune, in the <hi>.XXVIII.</hi> yere of the reygne of our moſt drad ſoueraine lord kyng <hi>HENRY</hi> the <hi>.VIII.</hi> and there continued and kepte tyll the diſſolution of the ſame parliament the <hi>.XVIII.</hi> of Iuly, to the honour of God, and for the common weale and profyt of this realme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THO. BERTHELET RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIS IMPRESSOR EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVDEBAT, CVM PRIVILEGIO.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N acte that felons abiuring for pety treaſon, murder, or felony, ſhall not be admitted to the benefite of their clergie. <label>cap. i.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for continuinge of two ſtatutes made in the laſt parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, touchyng ſuche as go away with caſkettes, iewels, goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or plate of their maiſters. <label>capit. ii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte giuinge the kinges highnes auctoritie newely to allotte the towne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes in the ſhyres and marches of Wales, at any time within .iii. yeres nexte enſuing. <label>capi. iii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte repellyng the ſtatute lately made for the bringing in of doulas and lockerams. <label>cap. iiii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for auoydynge of exactions taken vpon prentyces in the cities bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes and townes corporate. <label>cap. v.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for continuaunce of the ſtatutes for beggers and vacabundes, and agaynſt conueiaunce of horſes and mares oute of this realme, agaynſte Walſhemen, makynge affrayes in the counties of Herff. Glou. and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and aganſt the vice of buggery. <label>cap. vi.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An act for the eſtabliſhment of the ſucceſſion of the imperial crowne of this realme. <label>cap. vii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for contynuaunce of the ſtatute ayenſte the cariage of braſſe latenne and copper out of this realme: and for makynge of cables and ropes: for the wyndyng of wolles, and ayenſt kyllyng of weinlinges vnder the age of two yeres. <label>cap. viii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for continuaunce of the ſtatutes of periury, for makynge of iayles, for peuterers, and for ſowynge of flaxe and hempe. <label>cap. ix.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte extynguyſhynge the auctoritie of the byſhop of Rome. <label>cap. x.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for reſtitution of the fyrſte fruites in tyme of vacation to the nexte Incumbent. <label>cap. xi.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte declarynge the lymyttes of the kynges palays of Weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <label>cap. xii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte compellynge ſpirituall perſons to kepe reſydence vpon theyr bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. <label>cap. xiii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte limitting the pryces of wynes. <label>cap. xiiii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for puniſhement of pirotes and robbers on the ſea. <label>capit. xv.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte for the releaſe of ſuche as haue opteyned pretended lycences and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations from the ſea of Rome. <label>cap. xvi.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte giuynge auctoritie to ſuche as ſhal ſuccede to the crowne of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, whan they come to the age of .xxiiii. yeres, to make fruſtrate ſuche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes as ſhall be made before in theyr tyme. <label>cap. xvii.</label>
               </item>
               <item>An acte concernyng treaſon in certayne caſes. <label>cap. xviii.</label>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS TABVLAE.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:2"/>
            <head>¶ An acte that felons abiuringe for pety treaſon, murder, or felony, ſhall not be admytted to the benefyte of theyr clergie. Capi. i.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the laſte parliament begonne and holden at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the third day of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges mooſte gratious reygne,<note place="margin">Abiuration.</note> and from thens adiourned to Weſtmynſter, and there holden and continued by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſondry prorogations, It was enacted amonges other thynges, that ſuch perſone and perſones,<note place="margin">Sainctuary</note> which dyd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee or reſorte to any paryſhe church, cimitory, or other lyke halowed place for tuition of his lyfe, by occaſion of any murder robberye or other felony by the ſame perſon commytted, and thervpon confeſſed any murder felony or other offence before a crowner: for the whiche the ſame perſone by the lawe of this realme afore that tyme vſed, ſhulde abiure and paſſe out of this realme, ſhulde be dyrected by the crowner to take his abiuratyon to any one ſaynctuary, being within this realme, which the ſame perſon wold decte and choſe, there to remayne as a ſaintuary man abiured, duringe his naturall lyfe. And if after ſuch abiuration, any perſon ſo abiured, came out of the ſame ſaynctuarye, to the which he was aſſygned, and be taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſame ſaynctuary, not hauynge the kinges ſpeciall pardon or licence ſo to do, that then euery ſuch perſonne abiured, and after abiuration taken without ſaynctuarye, whervnto he was aſſigned, ſhuld ſuffre lyke peyne of deathe, and after lyke maner ſhuld be ordered, as he ſhuld haue done and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den, in caſe he had abiured this realme for murder or felony, and after ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che abiuration had returned agayne into this realme, contrarye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of this land. And it was further ordeined by the ſame acte, that if any ſuch ſaynctuary perſonne ſo abiured, or any other perſonne or perſonnes, which then were, or at any tyme after ſhuld happen to be in any ſainctuary of this realme, for doinge of any pety treaſon murder or felonye, or for being acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye to any ſuch offences: or if any perſone or perſons, which at any time after the making of the ſame acte, ſhuld take, any ſayntuary of this realme for any pety treaſon murder or felony, or for beinge acceſſary to any ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fences, or vpon abiuration: and ſo being in ſainctuary for any ſuch cauſe matter or offence, afterward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any pety treaſon murder or felony with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame ſainctuarie, or be acceſſarie to any ſuch offences, or goo oute of the ſame ſainctuarie, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte any petye treaſon, murder or felonye, or be acceſſary to any ſuch offences, and afterward come again to the ſame ſainctuarie, or take any other ſainctuarie for the ſame: that euery ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons, beinge indited for any of the ſaid cauſes or offences, ſhuld loſe the priuilege of the ſaintuary by him taken, and of euery other ſaintu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary within this realme for any ſuch cauſe of pety treaſon, murder, felony, or abiuration, or for any acceſſary to any ſuche offences.</p>
            <p>¶And it was further ordeyned by the ſame acte, that al foreine plees, tria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by countrey, whiche ſhulde be pleded by any perſon or perſons array<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:150869:3"/> vpon any inditement for any pety treaſon, murder, or felonye, ſhuld be tried before the ſame Iuſtices, afore whom ſuch perſonnes ſhuld be array<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by the ſame iurours of the countie, that ſhal trie the petye treaſon murder or felony,<note place="margin">Challenge</note> without any further reſpite or delaie, And that no perſon arrayned for any pety treaſon, murder, or felony, ſhulde be admitted to any paremptorye challenge aboue the noumbre of .xx. which acte was made to endure to the ende of the nexte parliament, as by the ſaid act amonges di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers clauſes &amp; prouiſions conteined in the ſame more plainely is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>¶And where alſo in the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it was enacted, that no perſon or perſons, which ſhuld happen to be founde giltie after the lawes of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, for any maner of petye treaſon, or for any wilfulle murder of malice prepenſed, or for robbinge of any churches, chapelles, or other holie places, or for robbyng of any perſonne or perſonnes, in theyr dwellinge houſes or dwellinge place, the owner or dweller in the ſaide houſe, his wife, his chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or ſeruauntes then beinge within, and putte in feare and drede by the ſame: Or for robbing of any perſon or perſons in or nere about the highe wayes, or for wilfull bourninge of any dwellinge houſes or bernes, wherin any corn or graine ſhal happen to be: nor that any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, being founde giltie of any abbetrement; procurement, helpinge, maynteyning, or counſaylinge of or to any ſuch petie treaſon,<note place="margin">Benefyt of clergy.</note> murders, or felonies, ſhuld be admitted to the benefyte of theyr clergye (ſuche as be within holy orders, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, of the orders of ſubdeacon or aboue, all onely except) with many other clauſes and prouiſions conteined in the ſaid acte, as by the ſame acte more playnely appereth: which acte was alſo made to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue and endure to the laſte daye of the nexte parlyament.</p>
            <p>¶And where alſo in the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it was further enacted, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch perſone and perſons, which ſhulde happen to be indited of any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty treaſon, wilfull burninge of houſes, murder, robberie, or burgularye, or other felonye, accordinge to the tenour and meaninge of the ſaid eſtatute nexte aboue reherſed,<note place="margin">Standynge muet.</note> and thervpon arrained, didde ſtande muet of malice, or froward minde, or challeng paremptorie aboue the numbre of .xx. or els will not anſwere directely to the ſame inditement and felony, whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal be arrayned: that then euery ſuche perſon and perſones, ſhuld loſe the benefite and priuilege of theyr clergie.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND IT VVAS ALSO ORDEYNED</hi> by the ſame acte, that if any perſon or perſones, be indited and founde giltie for ſtealing of any goodes or cattelles, in any countie of this realme, or beinge indited, ſtande muet of malyce, or chalenge paremptorie aboue the numbre of .xx. perſonnes, or will not aunſwere directely to the lawe, ſhuld alſo loſe the benefite of theyr clergie, in like maner and fourme as they ſhulde haue doone, if they hadde be endyted, arrayned, and founde gyltye in the ſame countie, where the ſame robberie or burgulary was doone, if it ſhall appere to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſtices, by euidence or examination, that the ſaide felons or robbers arayned afore them, ſhuld or ought to haue loſte theyr clergie by force of the ſaid eſtatute
<pb facs="tcp:150869:3"/> in caſe they hadde be founde gyltie of the ſame felonies or burglaries, in the ſame ſhyre where they were commytted, as by the ſayde acte amonges other thinges more at large is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>¶And where alſo in the ſayde parlyament it was further ordeyned, that the deteſtable vice of buggery, commytted with mankynde or beaſte,<note place="margin">Buggery. Felony.</note> ſhoulde be felony, and that the offenders therin ſhulde loſe the priuilege of theyr clergy: whiche acte was made to endure to the laſte daye of the nexte parlyamente, as by the ſame acte amongeſte other thinges it appereth more at large. For as moche as the ſayde actes, be beneficiall and profitable for the common welthe of this realme, Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyamente, that the ſayde actes and euery of theym, and all clauſes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions conteyned in the ſame, ſhall ſtande in full ſtrengthe and vertue, and from henſeforthe to continue and endure vnto the laſt daye of the nexte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament.</p>
            <p>¶And alſo be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſayd, that ſuche as be within ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly orders, ſhall from henſeforth ſtande and be vnder the ſame peines and daungers for the offences conteyned in any of the ſayde ſtatutes,<note place="margin">Orders.</note> and be vſed and ordered to all intentes and purpoſes, as other perſons not beynge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in holy orders: Any prouiſion or exception ſpecified in any of the ſayd actes, or any other vſage or cuſtome of this realme to the contrary therof not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. This acte to endure vnto the laſt day of the next parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte for continuing of two ſtatutes made in the laſt parlyament tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge ſuche as go awaye with caſkettes, iewels, goodes, or plate of theyr mayſters. Cap. ii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the laſte parlyamente begonne and holden at Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don, the third day of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges mooſt gracious reygne, and from thenſe adiourned to Weſtmynſter, and there holden and continued by diuers prorogations vnto the diſſolution therof, it was ordeined &amp; enacted amongeſt other thinges, that yf any ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">Seruantes, Caſkettes, Iewels.</note> to whome any caſkettes iewels money goodes or catalles, ſhulde be deliuered to kepe by his or theyr maiſters or maiſtreſſes, doo go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with the ſaide caſkettes, iewels, money, goodes, or cacalles, or any parte therof, to the intente to ſteale the ſame, and defraude his or their ſaide maiſter or mayſtres therof, contrary to the truſte and confidence to him or them putte by his or their ſaide maiſters or maiſtreſſes: Or elles being in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce without aſſente or commaundemente of his ſaide maiſter or mayſtres embeſile the caſkettes, iewelles, money, goodes, or cattalles,<note place="margin">Embeſiling.</note> of his ſaid mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or maiſtreſſe, or any parte therof, or otherwyſe conuerte the ſame to his owne vſe, with lyke purpoſe to ſteale, than if the ſaide caſkets, iewels, money, goodes, or cattalles, that any ſuche ſeruaunte ſhall go awaye with or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he ſhall embeſyle with pourpoſe to ſteale it (as is afore ſayde) be of the
<pb facs="tcp:150869:4"/> value of .xl.s. or aboue: that then the ſame falſe fraudulent and vntrewe acte and demeanour ſhould from henſeforth be demed and adiudged felony. And that he or they ſo offendyng,<note place="margin">Felony.</note> ſhould be puniſhed as other felons be puniſhed for felony commytted by courſe of the common lawe, whiche acte was then made to endure to the next parliament.</p>
            <p>¶And where alſo in an other acte made in the ſayde parlyament, it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that if any ſeruaunte for the tyme beyng in ſeruyce with any perſon or perſons, happen to ſteale, or felonouſely take awaye any iewels money plate or other goodes or cattalles of his maiſter or mayſtreſſe: or if any ſeruaunt, to whome any caſkette iewels money goodes or cattalles were delyuered by his mayſter or mayſtreſſe, and goo awaye with the ſayde caſket money goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or cattalles, or any parte therof, contrarye to the truſte and confydence to hym or theym putte: or withoute the aſſente or commaundemente of his ſayde mayſter or maſtreſſe embeſile any caſkette, iewelles, money, goodes, or cattalles, or any parte therof, or otherwyſe conuerte the ſame to his owne vſe, with pourpoſe to ſteale it, if the ſayde caſkette, money, iewels, goodes, or other cattalles, be of the value of .xl.s. or aboue: that then the offendour in ſuche caſe ſhould loſe the benefitte of his clergye,<note place="margin">Benefite of clergy. Sainctuary.</note> and the priuilege of al ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaryes, as by the ſayde ſeuerall actes more playnly appereth. For as moche as the ſayd actes be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought neceſſary for the common welth of this realme, Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parlyament, that the ſame actes, and euery of theym, and al and euery clauſe article and prouiſo therin conteyned, ſhall from henſeforth ſtand good &amp; endure and continue for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>An acte gyuynge the kinges hyghnes auctoritie newly to allotte the towne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppes in the ſhyres and marches of wales, at any tyme with in three yeres next enſuynge. Cap. iii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Here in the parlyamente begonne and holden at London the thyrde daye of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the reygne of oure mooſte drad ſoueraygne lorde kynge Henry the .viii. and frome thenſe adiourned to Weſtmynſter, and there holden and conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by dyuers prorogations vnto the .iiii. daye of Februarye, in the .xxvii. yere of the reygne of our ſayde ſoueraygne lorde, and then and there holden and continued vnto the dyſſolution therof, one acte and ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was made in the ſeſſion of the ſayde parlyament, holden the ſayde .iiii. day of Februarie,<note place="margin">Shires newly made in Wales.</note> wherby amonges other thynges dyuers ſhyres and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were newely made and named within the dominion and principalitie of wales, and dyuers townes paryſhes lordeſhyppes commotes and cantredes within the ſayde dominion and principalitie, were allotted appoynted &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the ſaid ſeueral ſhires and counties, as by the ſame act more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly amonges other thinges appereth. And for as moche as by credable information it is commen to the kinges knowledge ſythens the makinge of the ſayde acte, that ſome lordeſhyppes, townes, paryſhes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:4"/> hundredes, and cantredes, be not indyfferently allotted and lymyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſhires named in the ſayde acte, for the commoditie of the kynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectes therin inhabyted: Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente parlyament, that the kynges hyghnes (durynge the tyme of thre yeres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t after the ende of this preſent parlyament) ſhall haue power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by wrytynge vnder his great ſeale,<note place="margin">Allottyng of townſhyps in Wales.</note> to allotte appoynte aſſygne and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te to euery of the ſhires named in the ſayde acte, ſuche and ſo many lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyps townes pariſſhees hamlettes hundredes commotes and cantredes, as his maieſtie by his moſte highe wiſedome ſhall thinke moſte conuenient and agreable for the eaſe and commoditie of his louinge ſubiectes the inhabitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his ſayde dominion and principalitie.<note place="margin">Principalitie of Wales.</note> And ſhall lykewyſe haue power and auctoritie to name and aſſygne the ſhyre townes in euerye of the ſayde ſhires named in the ſayde acte. And that euery ſuche limitation apointment nomination and aſſignement to be made by the kynges hyghnes in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, by auctoritie of this acte, ſhall be as good and effectuall to all intentes and purpoſes, as thoughe it had bene done and made playnely and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by auctoritie of parliament: any thyng conteyned in the ſayd acte, made in the laſt parliament, or any other thynge or thinges to the contrary therof notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte repellyng the ſtatute lately made for the bringing in of doulas and lokerams. Cap. iiii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter the third daye of Nouember, in the .xxi. yere of the reigne of our ſoueraygne lorde king Henry the .viii. amongeſt other thinges it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted and eſtabliſhed, that no perſon nor perſons, engliſhe nor ſtraunger, deniſen or alien, from or after the feaſte of ſaincte Mighel tharchangel than next folowyng, ſhuld bryng or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uey, or cauſe to be conueied or brought by any maner of meanes into this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of England, any linnen clothe, called doulas or lockerams,<note place="margin">Doulas and lockerams.</note> on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es euery hole piece of doulas conteined in length fyue ſcore elles of aſſiſe, accompted to euery elle, one inche of aſſiſe, and in bredth one yarde of aſſiſe: And euery halfe piece fyfty elles in lengthe, and one yarde in bredth of lyke aſſiſe, and al the hole piece and half piece of one goodnes in making. And alſo it was there enacted and eſtablyſhed, that euery hole piece of lockerams ſhulde be of lyke length, as the hole piece of doulas: and euery halfe piece of lockerams ſhuld be of lyke length as the halfe piece of doulas: and euery ſuch hole piece and halfe piece of lockerams to be in bredth a hole yarde, lackyng a nayle of the yarde: and euery piece and halfe piece to be in lyke goodnes by all the length of the ſame piece, vppon peyne of forfeyture of the ſame doulas and locke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rams ſo to be brought or conueyed into this realme, not conteynyng the full lengthe bredth and goodnes, or the value therof, as in the ſame ſtatute more playnely at large doth appere. Sithens the makyng of whiche acte a greate
<pb facs="tcp:150869:5"/> nombre of kinges ſubiectes, that is to ſaye, weauers, tuckers, ſpynners, dyers, and wulpikers, and many others haue bene ydell and without worke, to theyr great impoueryſſhynge, whiche more and more is lyke dayly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creace, if remedy be not prouyded, for as moche as the clothemakers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che before the makynge of the ſayde acte, were wonte to conuey theyr ſayde clothes into Britaine, where the ſayde lynnen clothe called doulas and loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerams is made, and from thenſe to brynge with theym the ſayde lynnen clothe called doulas and lockeram, whiche they canne not doo ſythens the makynge of the ſayde acte, without daunger and forfayture of the ſayde lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothe by reaſon that there ſhall noo engliſhe man be ſuffered to carye or conuey any of the ſayde clothes, called doulas or lockerams, from the parties of beyonde the ſea into this realme of the length conteyned in the ſayde acte: whiche wyl make the ſayde cloth makers to leue the makynge of theyr cloth, to the greatte and manyfolde perylles of the kynges ſubiectes: Be it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enacted by the kynge oure ſoueraygne lorde, with the aſſente of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parlyament aſſembled, and by the auctoritie of the ſame, that the ſayde acte, made in the ſayde .xxi. yere, be to all intentes pourpoſes and conſtructions in the lawe, made vtterly voyde and of none effecte, as yf this ſayde acte hadde neuer ben had nor made. Neuertheleſſe to the entent that the byers of the ſayde lynnen clothes, ſhall not at any tyme hereafter be deceiued by the length of the ſayd clothes. Be it therfore enacted by the auctoritie afore ſayd, that after the feaſt of ſayncte Myghell the archangell nexte commynge, no maner of perſonne englyſſhe nor ſtraunger, denyſen nor alyen, putte to ſale any hole piece or halfe piece of the ſayde lynnen clothe called doulas and lockerams, one leſſe there be mencion expreſſed vppon euery of the ſayde hole piece or halfe piece of the ſayde lynnen clothe called doulas or lockeram, ſo putte to ſale, as is aforeſayde, the hoole and entier noumbre of the yardes or elles, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in euerye ſuche hole piece or halfe piece, vppon peyne of forfeyture of the ſame hole piece or halfe piece, not conteynynge the noumbre of yardes or elles, ſo mencioned vpon euery of the ſayde hole piece or halfe piece, ſo put to ſale as is afore ſayde. The one halfe of euery ſuche forfayture to be to the kynge our ſoueraygne lorde, and the other halfe to hym that ſhall ſeaſe and wyll ſue for the ſame by action of det, byl, plaint, information, or otherwyſe: in whiche action, ſuite, or information, no wager of lawe nor eſſoyne ſhall be admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>¶Prouyded alwayes, that this acte or any thyng therin conteyned, be not preiudiciall ne hurtefull to any perſon or perſonnes, that before the fyrſt day of this parlyamente, hath made any ſeaſer, or putte in any information, in to any of the kynges courtes, for any maner of forfayture, doone or commytted by any perſon or perſonnes, contrarye to the ſayde eſtatute, made in the ſaide thyrde daye of Nouembre, the .xxi. yere of the reygne of our ſoueraygne lorde kynge Henry the eyght.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:5"/>
            <head>¶An acte for auoydinge of exactions taken vpon prentices in the cities boroughes and townes corporate. Cap. v.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begonne at London the third day of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the reigne of our moſte drad ſoueraigne lorde king Henry the .viii. and from thens ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourned and proroged vnto weſtminſter, the .xvi. day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuary, in the .xxii. yere of the reigne of our ſaid ſoueraigne lorde, and there then alſo holden. It was &amp; is recited, that where before that time it was eſtabliſhed &amp; enacted in the .xix. yere of our late ſoueraigne lorde king Henry the .vii. that no maiſter wardeynes and felowſhippe of craftes, or any of them, nor any rulers of the gyldes or fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ities ſhuld take vpon them to make any actes or ordinaunces, ne to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecute any actes or ordinaunces by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before that time made, or then here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be made, in diſheritance or diminutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prerogatiue of the king, nor of other, nor againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon profite of the people: but if the ſame actes or ordinaunces were examined or approued by the Chancellour, trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſorer of England, or chief iuſtice of either bench, or thre of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or before the Iuſtices of aſſiſe in their circuite or progres, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhire where ſuch actes or ordinaunces be made, vpon peyn of forfaiture of .xl. fi. for euery time that they do the contrary, as more plainely in the ſaid acte doth appere.<note place="margin">wardenies of felowſhyps.</note> Syth which tyme diuers wardens and felowſhips haue made actes &amp; ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that euery prentice ſhuld pay at his firſt entre in their common hall to the wardens of the ſame felowſhip,<note place="margin">Apprentice.</note> ſomme of them .xl. ſ. ſome .xxx. ſ. ſome xi. ſ. ſome .xiii. ſ .iiii. d. ſome .vi. ſ .viii. d. ſom .iii. ſ .iiii. d. after their owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter mindes and pleaſure, contrary to the meaning of the ſaid act, made in the ſaid .xix. yere of the reigne of the ſaid late kinge Henry the .vii. and to the great hurte of the kinges true ſubiectes, putting their children to be prentiſes. It was therfore in the ſaid parliament, holden at weſtminſter in the ſaid .xxii. yere of the reigne of kyng Henry the .viii. eſtabliſhed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the kinge our ſoueraigne lord,<note place="margin">Fraternitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> by the aduiſe of his lordes ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall, and of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in the ſame parliament aſſembled, &amp; by the auctoritie of the ſame, that no maiſter wardeines or felowſhips of craftes, or maiſters, or any of them, nor any rulers of fraternities, ſhulde take from thenſforth of any prentice or of any other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entre of any prentice into their ſaid felowſhip, aboue the ſome of .ii. ſ .vi. d. nor for his entree whan his yeres and terme is expired and ended, aboue iii. ſ .iiii. d. vpon peyne of forfaiture of .xl. li. for euery time that they doo to the contrary, the one halfe to the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halfe to the partie that therfore ſhall ſue by action of dette informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or otherwiſe, and that in the action afore ſaide no protection or eſſoyne ſhalbe allowed: As by the ſame act amonges other thinges therin contey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned more playnely may appere. Sithen whiche ſayde ſeuerall actes eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſſhed and made (as is afore ſaide) diuers maiſters wardeines and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippes
<pb facs="tcp:150869:6"/> of craftes, haue by cautel and ſubtil meanes compaſſed and practiſed to defraude and delude the ſaid good and holſom ſtatutes, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge dyuers prentiſes or yonge men immediatly after their yeres be expy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or that they be made free of their occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or felowſhip, to be ſworne vpon the holy Euangeliſt at their firſt entre, that they ne any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after their yeres or terme expired, ſhall not ſet vp or open any ſhoppe houſe nor ſellar, nor occupie as freemen, without the aſſent and licence of the maiſter wardens or felowſhippes of their occupations, vpon peine of forfaitinge theyr freedome, or other like penaltie. By reaſon wherof the ſaid prentices &amp; iourney men be put to as moch or more charges therby then they before time were put vnto for the obteininge and entering of their fredom, to the great hurt and impoueriſhement of the ſaide prentices and iourney men, and other their frendes. For remedie wherof be it now, by the auctoritie of this preſent parliament eſtabliſſhed, ordeined, and enacted, that no may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wardens or felowſhippes of craftes, nor any of them, nor any rulers of fraternities gildes or brotherhedes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henſforth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel or cauſe any pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice or iourney ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oth or bond heretofore made or hereafter to be made, or otherwiſe, that he after his apprentiſhip or terme expired, ſhall not ſet vp nor kepe any ſhop houſe or ſellar,<note place="margin">Iourney ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> nor occupie as a free man without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the mayſter wardeines or felowſhip of his or their occupation, for and concerning the ſame, nor by any meane exact or take of any ſuch pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice or iourney men, nor any other occupieng for them ſelf, nor of any other perſons for them, after his or their ſaid yeres expired, any ſum of money or other thinges for or concerning his or their fredome, or occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, other wiſe or in any other maner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before is recited limitted &amp; appointed in the ſaid former acte, made in the ſaid .xxii. yere of the reigne of king Henry the viii. vpon the peyne to forfaite for euery time that they or any of them ſhal offend contrary to this acte .xl.li. The one half therof to the king our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne lorde, &amp; the other half to the partie that wil ſue for the ſame in any of the kinges courtes, by actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of det, informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or otherwiſe: in which ſuite or action no protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor eſſoine ſhalbe allowed for the partie defendant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte for continuance of the ſtatutes for beggers &amp; vacabundes and againſt conueyaunce of horſes and mares out of this realme, ageinſt Welſhe men making affrayes in the counties of Herff. Glouc. and Salop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and againſt the vice of buggery. Cap. vi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begonne at London the third day of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the reigne of our moſt drad ſoueraigne lorde king Henry the .viii. and from thenſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourned to weſtmynſter, and there holden and continued by prorogation vnto the .xvi. day of Ianuarie in the .xxii. yere of our ſaide ſoueraine lord, it was then in that ſeſſion of the ſaide parliament, an acte made and eſtabliſhed, declaring and concerning
<pb facs="tcp:150869:6"/> as well how aged, poore, and impotent perſonnes,<note place="margin">Vagab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> compelled to lyue by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs ſhoulde be ordered, as howe vacabundes and myghty ſtrong beggers ſhuld be whipped and puniſhed: whiche acte was then made to endure and continue vntyll the laſt daye of the nexte parliament. And where alſo in the ſaid ſeſſion of the ſayd parliament, one other acte was made for the reſtraint of carieng and conueyinge of horſes and mares out of this realme,<note place="margin">Horſes and mare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whiche acte was alſo made to continue and endure to the laſt daye of the nexte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament, as by the ſaid two ſeueral actes more plainly appereth. And where alſo at the ſayde parliament continued and proroged vnto the thyrde day of Nouembre, in the .xxvi. yere of the reygne of our ſayde ſoueraygne lorde, it was then in that ſeſſion of the ſayd parliament,<note place="margin">welſhemen.</note> an other acte made and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhed, for punyſhement of welſhemen, attemptynge aſſaultes or affrayes vpon any the inhabitauntes of Hereforde, Glouceſtre, Shropſhyre, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che acte was alſo made to endure vnto the laſt day of the next parlyament, as by the ſayde acte more plainely appereth. And where alſo in the ſayd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament, contynued and proroged vnto the .xv. daye of Ianuary, in the .xxv yere of our ſayde ſoueraigne lord, it was then in that ſeſſion of the ſayd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament one other acte made and eſtablyſhed for puniſhement of the vyce of buggery, declarynge ſuche offence to be felony,<note place="margin">Buggery.</note> whyche acte was than alſo made to endure to the laſt daye of the next parlyament, as by the ſayde acte more plainely appereth. For as moche as the ſayde .iiii. ſeueral actes be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall and profitable for the common weale of this realme, Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that the ſaid .iiii. actes and euery of them, and al clauſes, articles, and prouiſions therin conteined, ſhall from henſforth be obſerued and kept, and continue and endure vnto the laſt day of the nexte parlyament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte for the eſtablyſhement of the ſucceſſion of the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall crowne of this realme. Capi. vii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N their moſt humble wyſe ſhewen to your moſte royal maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the lordes ſpiritual and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mporal, and al other your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge and obedyente ſubiectes, the commons in this your moſt high court of parliament aſſembled, that where in your laſte parliament, begonne and holden at London the thirde daye of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of your mooſte gracious reygne, and from thens adiorned to Weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and there holden and contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by dyuers and ſundry prorogations vnto the .xv. daye of Ianuary, in the xxv. yere of your mooſte noble reygne, and than there holden, It was made and ordeyned an acte concernynge amonges many thynges; as wel for rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and confyrmation of your maryage,<note place="margin">Lady Anne Boleine.</note> than hadde and ſolempnyſed betwene your hyghnes and the late lady Anne Boleyne Marques of Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, as for the lymittation of the ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your imperial crowne of this realme, to the iſſue of your body begoten &amp; to be begoten of the body of the
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:7"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:8"/> ſayde ladye Anne, with diuers remaynder ouer for defaute of ſuche iſſue, as in the ſaid acte playnely &amp; particularly more at large is expreſſed and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned.<note place="margin">Othe.</note> And where alſo by the ſayde acte it was ordeyned and eſtablyſſhed, that all and ſyngular your ſubiectes ſhuld take a corporal othe for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyllynge, maynteynynge, and defendynge, the hole effectes and contentes of the ſayde acte. And it was further ordeyned by the ſayde acte amonges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, that if any perſon or perſonnes, ſubiecte or reſiant within this realme, or within any your gracis dominions, after the fyrſt daye of Maye than nexte enſuynge, by wrytynge, prynte, dede, or acte procured or dyd, or cauſed to be procured or done any thyng or thynges to the preiudice, ſclan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, dyſturbance, or derogation of the ſayd matrymony, ſolemniſed bitwen your maieſtie and the ſayd lady Anne, or to the peryl, ſclaunder, or diſheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any the iſſues and heyres of your hyghneſſe beynge lymytted by the ſame acte to inherite &amp; to be inheritable to the crowne of this realme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any ſuche iſſues or heires of your hyghnes myghte be deſtroyed, diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or interrupted in bodye or title of inheritance to the crowne of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, as to them is lymytted in the ſame acte: that than euery ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſonnes, and theyr aydours, counſaylours, maynteynours, and abbettours, and euery of them, for euery ſuche offence, ſhoulde be adiudged hyghe traytours, and that euery ſuche offence, ſhuld be adiuged high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And the offendours and their aydours, counſaylours, maynteynours, and abettours, and euery of them, beynge lawefully conuycte of ſuche of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by preſentment, verdicte, confeſſion, or proceſſe, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and lawes of this realme, ſhulde ſuffre peynes of death, as in caſes of hyghe treaſon: as in the ſaid acte amonges many other articles, clauſes, and prouiſions, is more at large mencioned and ſpecified.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND</hi> alſo in the ſayd parlyamente holden at Weſtmynſter by proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the thyrde daye of Nouembre, in the .xxvi. yere of your mooſte noble reygne, an other acte was made for declaration and ratification of the ſayd othe, whiche dyuers of your ſubiectes then hadde taken, and all your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes after that were bounde to take for due obſeruation of the ſayd acte of the ſayde Succeſſion,<note place="margin">Succeſſion.</note> as by the ſame acte amonges other thinges is alſo ſpecified and expreſſed. And all be it moſte dradde ſoueraygne lorde, that the ſayde actes were thenne made, as it was then thoughte by your maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, nobles and commons, vpon a pure perfite and clere foundation, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the ſayde mariage then had betwene your highnes and the ſayd lady Anne in theyr conſciences to haue ben pure ſincere perfite and good, and ſo was reputed, accepted, and taken in the realme, tyll nowe of late, that god of his infinite goodnes (frome whom noo ſecrete thynges canne be hydde) hath cauſed to be broughte to lyghte euidente and open knowledge, as well certayne, iuſte, trewe and lawefulle impedimentes vnknowen at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the ſayde actes, and ſithen that time confeſſed by the ſayde ladye Anne, before the mooſte reuerende father in god Thomas Archebyſſhoppe of Canturburye, Metropolytane and prymate of all Englande, ſyttynge
<pb facs="tcp:150869:8"/> iudicially for the ſame: by the which plainely appereth, that the ſaid mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age betwene your grace and the ſaid lady Anne, was neuer good nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ante to the lawes, but vtterly voyde and of none effecte. By reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, your highnes was &amp; is laufully deuorced and ſeperated from the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaid mariage in the lyfe of the ſaid ladye Anne. And this not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moſte gracious ſoueraine lord, the lady Eliſabeth your doughter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge borne vnder the ſaid vnlaufull mariage, by vertue and auctoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acte of your ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, for lacke of heires males of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſhuld immediately ſuccede as your lauful heire in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt roial eſtate of your imperiall crowne of this realme, gainſt all honour equitie reaſon and good conſcience, if remedy ſhuld not be prouided for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And ouer this moſt dradſouerayne lorde, al be it that your maieſtie not knowing of any lauful impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, entered into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes of the ſaid vnlauful mariage, &amp; auanced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame lady Anne to the honour of the ſoueraine eſtate of quene of this realme: yet neuer the leſſe ſhe inflamed with pride &amp; carnal deſires of her body, putting a part y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drede of god and excellent benefites receiues of your highnes, confederated her ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George Bolein late lord Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, her naturall brother, Henry Norreis eſquier, Fraunces weſton knight William Brereton eſquier, gentillmen of your priuie chaumbre, &amp; Marke S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ton Grome of your ſaid priuie chaumbre, &amp; ſo being confederated, ſhe and they mooſte traiterouſely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted and parpetrated diuers deteſtable and abhominable treaſons, to the moſte fearefull perill and daunger of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>truction of your moſt roiall perſon, and to the vtter loſſe diſheriſon and deſolation of this realm, if god of his goodnes had not in due tim brought theyr ſaid treaſons to light: for the which being palmely and manyfeſtely proued, they were conuicte &amp; atteinted by the due courſe and order of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes of this realme, and haue ſuffered accordynge to theyr mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tts, as by the recordes therof more at large maye appere.</p>
            <p>¶And al be it moſt gratious and moſt dred ſoueraine lorde, diuers &amp; ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry honourable iuſt true and reſonable clauſes be conteyned &amp; expreſſed in the ſaid act, made for the eſtabliſhement of your ſucceſſion, which be verye neceſſary and profitable for the common welthe of this realm: yet neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> les bycauſe certaine articles &amp; clauſes conteined in the ſame, concerninge the ratification of your ſaid vnlaufull mariage, betwene your highnes &amp; the ſaid ladye Anne, and the limittation of your ſucceſſion to the iſſues of your body had by the ſaide lady Anne, &amp; the othe expreſſed and mentioned in bothe the actes aboue remembred, for the defending and maynteinynge the holle effectes and contentes of the ſaide acte, whiche clauſes and arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles be nowe become of late ſo diſhonourable, and ſoo far diſtaunte from the due courſe of your common lawes of your realme, and alſo ſo moche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiſt good reaſon equitie and good conſcience, that they can not be ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor tollerated to continue &amp; endure without greatte perill of dyuiſion hereafter to be hadde by occaſion of the ſame, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges vs your ſaid mooſt humble louinge and obedient ſubiectes &amp; our poſterities. It may therfore
<pb facs="tcp:150869:9"/> pleaſe your highnes of your moſt excellent and accuſtomable goodnes, and for the entier loue fauour &amp; harty affection, that your maieſtie hath alwais borne and beareth to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthe of this your realm, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the good peace vnitie and reſte of vs your mooſte bounden, &amp; obediente ſubiectes, and of your ſaid poſterities, that it maye be enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parlyamente, that the ſaid two actes and euery of them, and al clauſes articles and prouiſions therin conteyned, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte daye of this preſent parliament, ſhall be repealed, adnulled, and made fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Repele.</note>¶Prouyded alwaye, that the ſaide repeale and adnullaion of the ſayde acte, which was made for the eſtablyſſhemente of your ſucceſſion, ſhall not be taken expounded nor vnderſtand, to diſcharg any perſone or perſonnes, which haue done or committed any offences of treaſon, or miſpriſion of tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, contrary to the ſame acte, or any parte therof, at any time afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte daie, of this preſente parliamente: but that ſuche offences of treaſon and miſpriſion of treaſon, done and committed by any perſonne or perſonnes, contrary to the ſame acte, afore the firſte daye of this preſent parliamente, ſhall be and remaine in the ſame degree &amp; qualitie to be puniſſhed by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of the ſame acte, as if the ſame acte hadde not ben repealed: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale and adnullation of the ſame acte by auctoritie of this preſent parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amente in any wyſe not withſtandinge. Neuer the laſſe the kynges moſte royall maieſtie, mooſte gratiouſelye conſyderynge, that diuers and manye of his mooſte louynge and obedyente ſubiectes nowe lately afore the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of this preſente parlyamente, haue ſpoken, doone, practyſed, procured, and attempted, as well by wordes wrytynge and pryntynge, as by exteriour actes, not onely againſt the ſaid vnlawefull mariage, ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed betwene his highneſſe and the ſaide ladye Anne, and to the preiudice ſclaunder diſturbance and derogation therof, but alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perill ſclaunder and diſheryſon of the ladye Elyſabeth the kynges daughter illegyttimate borne vnder the ſame mariage, and to the let diſturbaunce &amp; interruption of the ſaid ladye Elyſabeth to the title of the crowne: and alſo to depriue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid lady Anne late Quene, and the ſaid lady Elyſabeth, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr dignitie title and name of theyr roiall eſtates, contrarye to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours purportes prouiſions and ordynaunces, as well conteyned in the ſaid acte made in the laſte parliament for the eſtabliſhement of the kinges ſucceſſion, as in an other act made in the laſte parliament for puniſhement of treaſons. Which wordes doynges practiſes procurementes &amp; attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his ſaid ſubiectes, all be it they proceded of no malyce, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true and iuſte groundes, for punyſhement of the ſaid late lady Anne, according to her deſertes, and for reformation of the ſaide vnlaufull mariage, for the ſuretie of the kinges highneſſe, &amp; for the vnitie and welthe of this realme: yet neuertheleſſe the kinges ſaid ſubiectes mought hereafter happen to be empeched troubled and vexed for ſuch theyr wordes doinges actes procure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes and attemptes, as well by reaſon of the ſaid eſtatute, made for the
<pb facs="tcp:150869:9"/> eſtablyſhement of the kinges ſucceſſion, and nowe repealed by this act, as by occaſion of other ſtatutes heretofore made for puniſhment of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and miſpriſion of treaſon, to the greatte daunger and perylles of the liues lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and goodes of the kinges ſayde ſubiectes, which onely for harty good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>will and faithefull obedience, that they beare to the kinges maieſtie, incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the ſayd dangers and peryls: The kinges highnes thefore of his mooſt bountyfull mercy and benignitie is pleaſed and contented, that it be enacted by auctoritie of this preſente parliament, that all and ſingular his louynge ſubiectes, which haue ſpoken done practiſed commited or attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or procured to be done or attempted directely or indyrectely, by wordes,<note place="margin">Pardon.</note> writinges, printes, or any exterior acte, any thinge or thynges what ſo euer it be againſt the ſaid mariage, ſolempnyſed betwene his highneſſe and the ſaide late Quene Anne, or for the ſettinge forthe or preferremente of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce or diſſolution therof: or againſt the ſaid late quene Anne, or the ſaid lady Eliſabeth, or to any of theyr ſclaunders perilles, or diſheriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: or haue wiſhed willed or deſired by wordes or writinges, or inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted imagined prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed or attempted any bodily harme to the ſaid late quene Anne, or lady E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyzabeth, or to depriue the ſame late quene Anne, or ladye Elizabeth, or any of them, of the dignitie title or name of theyr royall eſtates, or haue ſpoken done or procured to be done any other wordes writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges printinges wiſhing willinge, thinge or thinges, acte or actes, againſt the ſaide late quene Anne or lady Elizabeth, which is or moughte be demed or interpreted for treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or miſpriſion of treaſon by any conſtruction vppon any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatutes of this realme heretofore made, ſhall be freely and clerely pardoned diſcharged &amp; releaſed by auctoritie of this act of al thoſe and ſuch treaſons, and miſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of treaſons aboue mencioned. And that none of his ſaid louing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes for any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid treaſons or miſpriſions of treaſon aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned and ſpecified, ſhal hereafter at any time, by any maner of meanes be empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vexed or troubled in theyr bodies liues la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des goodes or cattalles, any thinge in this act, or in any acte or actes heretofore made for treaſons or miſpriſons of treaſon, to the contrary therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶And that it be further enacted by auctoritie afore ſaide,<note place="margin">Atteinder of quene Anne, and other.</note> that the ſayde late Queene Anne, George Boleyn, late lorde Rocheforde, Henry Norreis eſquier, Fraunces Weſton knight, William Brereto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſquier, and Marke Smeton, for theyr abhominable and deteſtable treaſons, by them and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them mooſte abhominably and trayterouſly committed and done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your maieſtie &amp; the realme, ſhal be by auctoritie of this preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament conuicted and atteinted of high treaſon, in ſuche maner &amp; fourme and accordingelye as they be, by the dewe courſe and order of your lawes of this realme. And that the ſaide late Queene Anne, George lord Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, Henry Norreis, Fraunces Weſton, William Brereton, and Marke Smeton, and euery of them, ſhall loſe and forfaite to your highenes and to your heires, al ſuche theyr manours, meaſes, landes, tenementes, rentes, reuerſyons, remaynders, vſes, poſſeſſions, offices, ryghtes, condycions,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:10"/> and all other hereditamentes, of what names natures or qualyties ſo euer they be, which they or any of them, or any other to theyr vſes, or to the vſe of any of them had or ought to haue had of any eſtate of inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in fee ſymple or in fee taile, in vſe or poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of their ſeueral treaſons, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted limitted and expreſſed in theyr inditemente, or at any time after. Sauing to euery perſon &amp; perſons, and bodies politike, and to the heires aſſignes and ſucceſſours of euery of them (other than to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid late Quene Anne, and the other traytours afore named: and theyr heires and aſſignes of euery of them and all and euery other perſon &amp; perſons claiming by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of or any of them, or to theyr vſes, or to the vſes of any of them, or to the vſe of any of theyr heires) all ſuche right title vſe poſſeſſion intereſt condicion fees offices rentes annuites commons, and all other commodities and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes, what ſoo euer they or any of them moughte ſhulde or ought to haue had, if this acte had neuer ben had ne made.</p>
            <p>¶And ouer this moſte gracious ſoueraigne lorde, for as moche as it hath pleaſed your mooſte roiall maieſtie, not withſtandinge the great and intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable perils and occaſions, which your highnes hath ſuffered and ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as wel by occaſion of your firſte vnlaweful mariage ſolempniſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene your highneſſe and the lady Katheryne,<note place="margin">Princes Dowager</note> late princes dowager, as by occaſion of the ſaide vnlafull mariage betwene your highnes and the ſaid late queene Anne, at the moſt humble petition and interceſſion of vs your nobles of this realme, for the ardent loue and feruent affection, which your highnes beareth to the conſeruation of the peace and vnitie of the ſame, &amp; for the good and quiete gouernaunce therof, of your moſt excellente good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to entre in to mariage againe, and haue choſen &amp; taken a righte noble vertuous and excellent lady quene Iane to your trewe and lawefull wyfe,<note place="margin">Queene Iane.</note> and haue laufully cellebrated and ſolemniſed mariage with her, according to the lawes of holy church: Who for her conuenient yeres, excellent beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and pureneſſe of fleſſhe and bloudde, is apte (god willinge) to conceiue iſſue by your highneſſe: whiche mariage is ſoo pure and ſincere, withoute ſpotte doubte or impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the iſſue procreated vnder the ſame, whan it ſhal pleaſe almighty god to ſend it, can not be laufully trewely nor iuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interrupted or diſturbed of the ryghte and title in the ſucceſſyon of your crowne: It maye therfore nowe pleaſe your moſte gratious maieſtie, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſte humble petition and interceſſyon of vs your nobles and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aſſembled in this preſente parliamente, as well for the clere extinguiſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ambyguities and doubtes, as for a pure and perfecte vnitie of vs your moſte humble and obedient ſubiectes, and of all our poſteryties, that it maye be enacted by your moſte gratious and roiall maieſtie, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctoritie of the ſame in maner and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as hereafter in articles enſueth.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>FYRSTE FOR AS MOCHE</hi> as the maryage here to fore ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed betwene your hyghnes and the ſaid lady Katharine, late prynces do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wager
<pb facs="tcp:150869:10"/> deceaſed, whiche afore was lawefull wyfe to your naturall brother prynce Arthur, and by hym carnally knowen, as hath duly bene proued by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficient witneſſes, at al times was is and ought to be demed and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to be againſt the lawes of almighty god, &amp; not diſpenſable by any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine auctoritie, and ſo hath be demed and determined, as well by the hole clergie of this realme, in both conuocations, and by bothe the vniuerſities therof, as by the vniuerſities of Bonony, Padua, Paris, Orleaunde, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, Angiew, and diuers other, &amp; alſo by a great nombre of priuate wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of many ryghte excellent well lerned men: Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſente parliamente, accordinge as it was ordeyned and enacted in the ſaid acte made in the laſt parlyament for the eſtablyſhement of your ſucceſſion, that the ſaid mariage heretofore hadde and ſolempniſed betwene your highneſſe and the ſaid lady Katherine, which was before lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wyfe, to the ſaid prince Arthur your elder brother, and by him carnally knowen, as doth dewely appere be ſufficient proue in a laufull proces had and made before the ſaid moſt reuerend father in god Thomas, by the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce of god archebiſſhoppe of Caunturburye, Metropolitane and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all England, ſhall be by auctoritie of this preſente parliament dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitiuely clerely and abſolutely declared demed &amp; adiudged to be againſt the lawes of almighty god, and alſo accepted reputed and taken of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue ne effect, but vtterly voide and adnichiled: And that the ſeperation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made by the ſaid archebiſhoppe ſhall be good and effectuall to all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and purpoſes, any licence, diſpenſation, or any other acte or actes going before or enſuinge the ſame, or to the contrarie therof in any wiſe not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge. And that euery ſuche lycence, diſpenſation, acte or actes, thynge or thinges, had made done or to be done to the contrary therof, ſhal be to al intentes voide and of none effecte, and ſo ſhall be reputed and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by and amonges al vs your true ſubiectes and inhabitauntes, our heires and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of and in your realme and dominions for euer. And that the iſſue borne and procreated vnder the ſame vnlaufull mariage, made &amp; ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwene your highnes and the ſaid lady Katherine, ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demed and accepted illegittimate to all intentes and pourpoſes, and ſhal be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forcloſed excluded and barred to claime chalenge or demaunde any inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytaunce as laufull heyre to your highneſſe by liniall diſſent.</p>
            <p>¶And alſo for as moche as the mariage ſolempniſed, betwene your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and the ſaid late quene Anne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true and iuſte cauſes was and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and adiudged by the ſaid moſt reuerende father, to be of noo value ne effecte, and a deuorce &amp; ſeperation therof hadde and made by the due order and proceſſe of the lawes of the churche of Englande, before the ſaid reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende father, Be it therfore enacted, by the auctoritie of this preſent parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame mariage betwene your highnes &amp; the ſaid late quene Anne, ſhall be taken reputed demed and adiudged to be of no force ſtrength ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue nor effecte: &amp; that the ſeparation and deuorce therof had by the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and iudgement of the ſaid moſt reuerende father, ſhal be good &amp; effectuall,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:11"/> and ſoo here after ſhall be taken and reputed for euer by al your ſubiectes, theyr heires and ſucceſſours. And that none appeale repeale reuocation or adnullation therof, or any part of the ſame, ſhall here after be hadde taken allowed or admitted in any behalfe. And that all the iſſues and childrene borne and procreated vnder the ſame mariage betwene your highneſſe and the ſaid late quene Anne, ſhall be taken reputed and accepted to be illegit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate to al intentes and purpoſes, and vtterly forcloſed excluded and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to clayme, challenge, or demaunde any inheritaunce as laufull heyre or heyres to your hyghnes by lyniall diſcent, the ſayd former acte made in the laſt parlyament, for the ſtablyſhement of your ſucceſſion, or any thing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contiyned, or any other thinge or thinges to the contrarye therof in any wyſe not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Degrees of mariage pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hybyted by goddes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</note>¶And further more ſyns many inconueniences haue fallen, as wel within this realme as in others, by reaſon of marieng within the degrees of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, prohibited by goddes lawes, that is to ſay, the ſonne to marye the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the ſtepmother carnally knowen by his father, the brother the ſiſter, the father his ſonnes daughter, or his daughters daughter: or the ſonne to marye the daugher of his father procreate and borne by his ſtepmother: or the ſon to mary his aunte, being his fathers or mothers ſiſter: or to mary his vncles wife carnally knowen by his vncle: or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father to mary his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wyfe carnally knowen by his ſon: or the brother to marye his brothers wyfe carnally knowen by his brother: or any man maryed, &amp; carnally kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge his wyfe, to marye his wyfes daughter, or his wifes ſonnes daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or his wyfes daughters daughter, or his wyfes ſyſter.</p>
            <p>¶And further to dilate and declare the meaning of theſe prohibitions, It is to be vnderſtand, that if it chaunce any man to knowe carnally any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">Prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mariage.</note> that then all and ſinguler perſonnes, beinge in any degree of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guynitie or affinitie, as aboue wrytten, to any of the parties ſo carnally of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendinge, ſhall be demed and adiudged to be within the caſes and limittes of the ſaid prohbiitions of maryage. All whiche mariages all be it they be playnely prohibite &amp; deteſted by the lawes of god, yet neuertheles at ſome times they haue proceded vnder colours of diſpenſations by mans power which is but vſurped, and of right oughte not to be graunted admitted ne, allowed. For no man, of what eſtate degree or condition ſo euer he be, hath power to diſpence with goddes lawes, as all the clergye of this realme in the ſaid conuocations, and the moſte parte of all the vniuerſyties of chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and we alſo do affyrme and thynke.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>BEIT</hi> therfore enacted by auctorytie afore ſayde, accordynge as it is declared and conteined in the ſaid acte, made in the laſt parliament for the eſtabliſhement of your ſucceſſion, that no perſon or perſons, ſubiectes or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyauntes of this realme, or in any your dominions, of what eſtate degree or dignitie ſo euer they be, ſhal from henſeforth mary within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degrees afore reherſed, what pretence ſo euer ſhall be made to the contrary therof. And in caſe any perſon or perſons, of what eſtate dignitie degree or condition ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:150869:11"/> they be, hath bene heretofore maryed within this realme, or in any other the kynges dominions, within any the degrees aboue reherſed, and by any the archebiſhoppes or miniſters of the church of England be ſeparate from the bondes of ſuch vnlaufull mariages: that then euery ſuche ſeperation ſhalbe good laufull fyrme and permanent for euer, &amp; not by any power au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie or meanes to be reuoked or vndone hereafter. And that the children proceding or procreate vnder ſuch vnlauful maryage, ſhal not be lauful ne legitimate: any foreyn lawes lycences diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſations, or other thing or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the contrary therof not withſtandinge. And that in caſe there be any perſon or perſons within this realme, or in any the kinges dominions al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy maried within any of the ſaid degrees aboue ſpecified, and not yet ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the bondes of ſuch vnlaufull mariage, that then euery ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo vnlaufully maried, ſhalbe ſeperate by the diffinitiue ſentence and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of the archebiſhops, biſhops, and other miniſters of the churche of Englande, and in other your dominions, within the limittes of their iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions &amp; auctorities, and by none other power or auctoritie. And that all ſentences and iugementes giuen and to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any archebiſhop biſhop or other miniſter of the church of Englande, or in any other the kinges do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, within the limittes of their iurisdictions and auctoritie, ſhall be diffinitiue firme good and effectuall to all intentes, and be obſerued, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, without ſuing any prouocations, appeles, prohibitions, or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, from or to the courte of Rome, to the derogation therof, or contrary to the acte made ſithen the beginninge of the laſt parliament for reſtrainte of ſuch prouocations, appeles, prohibitions, and other proceſſes.</p>
            <p>¶And alſo be it enacted by auctoritie afore ſaid, that all the iſſue hereafter to be had and procreate betwene your highnes, and your ſaid moſt dere and entierly beloued laufull wyfe Quene Iane, ſhall be your laufull children &amp; heires, and be inheritable and inherite, accordinge to the courſe of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and lawes of this realme, the imperiall crowne of the ſame, with all dignities, honours, preeminences, prerogatiues, auctorities, and iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the ſame annexed or belonging, in as large &amp; ample maner, as your highnes at this preſent time hath the ſame as king of this realme, the inhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritaunce therof to be and remayne to your ſaid children and right heyres in maner and fourme as here after ſhalbe declared, That is to ſay.</p>
            <p>¶Firſt the ſaid imperiall crowne and other the premiſſes, ſhalbe to youre maieſtie and to your heires of your body laufully begoten, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Eſtabliſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the kynges high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to the firſt ſonne of your body betwene your highnes and your ſaide lawefull wyfe quene Iane begoten, &amp; to the heires of the body of the ſame firſte ſon laufully begoten. And for defaute of ſuch heires, than to the ſeconde ſonne of your body, and of the body of the ſaid Quene Iane begoten, and to the heires of the body of the ſame ſeconde ſonne laufully begoten, as aforeſaid and ſo to euery ſonne of your body, and of the body of the ſaid quene Iane begoten, and to the heires of the body of euery ſuch ſon begoten, according to the courſe of inheritaunce in that behalfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:12"/>
            <p>¶And if it ſhall happen your ſaide moſte dere and entierly beloued wife quene Iane to deceaſe without iſſue male of the body of your highnes to be begoten (which god defende) then the ſame imperial crowne, and all other the premiſſes to be to your maieſtie, as is afore ſaid, and to the ſonne and heire male of your body laufully begotten by any other laufull wife, and to the heires of the body of the ſame ſonne &amp; heire male laufully begoten. And for defaute of ſuch iſſue, than to your ſecond ſonne of your bodye laufully begoten, and to the heyres of the body of the ſame ſecond ſonne laufully be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>goten: and ſo from ſonne and heire male, to ſonne and heire male, &amp; to the heires of the ſeuerall bodies of euery ſuch ſonne and heire male laufully be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>goten, according to the courſe of inheritaunce, in like maner and fourme, as is aboue ſaid.</p>
            <p>¶And for defaute of ſuch ſonnes of your body lawfully begotten: and of the heires of the ſeuerall bodies of euery ſuch ſonne laufully begoten, that thenne the ſaide imperiall crowne, and other the premiſſes, ſhall be to the iſſue female betwene your maieſtie and your ſaide moſte dere and entyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued wyfe Queene Iane begoten: And for lacke of ſuche iſſue, than to the heires females of your body, laufully begotten by any other lawfull wyfe: that is to ſaye: Firſte to the eldeſte iſſue female, and to the heyres of her bodie laufully begotten, and ſo from iſſue female to iſſue female, and to their heires of their bodies one after an other by courſe of inheritaunce, according to their ages, as the crowne of Englande hath ben accuſtomed and ought to ſuccede and go, in caſe when there is heire female inheritable to the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶And for as moche as it ſtandeth at this preſent time in the only pleaſure and wyll of almighty god, whether your maieſtie ſhal haue heires begoten and procreated betwene your highnes and your ſaid moſt dere and entierly beloued wyfe quene Iane, orelles any laufull heires and iſſues hereafter of your owne body begoten by any other laufull wife, and if ſuch heires ſhuld fayle (as god defende) and no prouiſion made in your life, who ſhulde rule and gouerne this realme for lacke of ſuch heires: that then this realme af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter your tranſitorie lyfe ſhall be deſtitute of a laufull gouernour: Or elles parcaſe encombred with ſuche a perſonne, that wolde couet to aſpire to the ſame, whome the ſubiectes of this realme ſhall not fynde in their hartes to loue drede and obediently ſerue as their ſoueraigne lorde. And if your grace afore it maye be certaynely knowen, whether ye ſhall haue heires or no, ſhulde ſodaynely name and declare any perſon or perſones to ſuccede after your deceaſe, and for lacke of heyres of your body lawefully begotten, into the royall eſtate of the imperiall crowne of this realme: thanne it is to be doubted, that ſuch perſon that ſhulde be ſo named, mought happen to take great harte and courage, and by preſumption fal to inobedience &amp; rebellion by occaſion of which premiſſes greate diuiſion and diſcention maye be and is very likely to ariſe and ſpringe in this realme, to the greate peryl and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of vs your moſte humble and obedyent ſubiectes, and of all oure
<pb facs="tcp:150869:12"/> poſterities, if remedie for the ſame ſhuld not be prouided. For reformation and remedie wherof, we your moſte bounden and louynge ſubiectes, moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently knowleginge, that your maieſtie moſt victoriouſly prudently po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kely and indifferently hath maynteyned defended gouerned and ruled this realme, in good peace reſt quietnes &amp; obedience, during all the time of your moſte gratious reigne, which we moſt hartely deſire moughte conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for euer, puttinge all oure hole truſte and confydence in youre highe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and nothinge doubtynge, but that your maieſtie, if ye ſhoulde faylle heyres of your body laufully begotten (which god defend) for the harty loue and feruent affection, that ye beare to this realme, and for auoydinge all the occaſions of diuiſion afore reherſed, ſo erneſtly mindeth the welth of the ſame, that ye can beſt and moſte prudently prouide ſuche a gouernour for vs and this your realme, as ſhall and will ſuccede and folowe in the iuſte and right trade of all your procedinges, and maynteyne kepe and defende the ſame, and all the lawes and ordinaunces eſtabliſſhed in your moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious tyme for the welth of this realme, which al we deſire, wherby we your ſaide moſte louinge and obedient ſubiectes, and our heires and ſucceſſours ſhal and may liue, as nere as may be, in as good peace vnitie &amp; obedience af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter your deceſſe, as we haue liued in the time of your moſt gratious reigne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o therfore moſt humbly beſeche your highnes, that it may be enacted, for auoyding of all ambiguities, doubtes deuiſions and occaſions in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, by your moſte royall maieſtie, by the aſſente of vs the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this your preſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctoritie of the ſame, that your highnes ſhal haue full and plenar power and auctoritie, to giue diſpoſe appoynte aſſigne declare and limitte by your letters patentes vnder your great ſeale, or elles by your laſte wyll made in writinge, and aſſigned with your moſt gratious hand, at your one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure from time to time, hereafter the imperial crowne of this realme and all other the premiſſes thervnto belonginge, to be remaine ſuccede and come after your deceaſe, and for lacke of laweful heyres of your body to be procreated and begotten as is afore limitted by this acte, to ſuch perſon or perſons in poſſeſſion and remaynder, as ſhal pleaſe your highnes, &amp; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to ſuch aſtate,<note place="margin">Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and after ſuch maner fourme facion order and condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ſhalbe expreſſed declared named and limitted in your ſaid letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, or by your ſaid laſte wyll. And we your moſte humble and obedient ſubiectes do faithfully promiſe to your maieſtie by one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aſſent, that after your deceaſſe &amp; for lacke of heires of your body laufully begotten, as is afore reherſed, we our heires and ſucceſſours ſhall accepte and take, loue drede ſerue and alonely obey ſuch perſon and perſons, males or females, as your maieſtie ſhal giue your ſaid imperial crown vnto by auctoritie of this act, and to none other, and holly to ſticke to them as true and faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes ought to do, to their regall rulers gouernours and ſupreme heades.</p>
            <p>¶And for ſure corroboration therof be it further enacted by auctoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaide, that ſuch perſon and perſones, as to whome it ſhall pleaſe your
<pb facs="tcp:150869:13"/> maieſtie to diſpoſe limitte and aſſigne your ſaid crowne, and other the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes therto apperteininge, by your letters patentes, or by your laſte wyll, as is aforeſaide, ſhall haue and enioye the ſame after your deceaſe, and for lacke of heires of your bodie lawfully begotten, according to ſuche aſtate, and after ſuch maner fourme facion order and condition, as ſhalbe therof expreſſed mentioned and conteyned in your ſaid letters patentes, or in your ſaid laſt will, in as large and ample maner, as if ſuch perſon and perſons had be your laufull heires to the imperiall crowne of this realme, and as if the ſame crowne of this realme had be giuen and limitted to them plainely and particularly by ſpecial names and ſufficient termes and wordes by the full and immediate auctoritie of this your moſt high court of parliament.</p>
            <p>¶And it is further enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid, that if any of your hey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res or children hereafter doo vſurpe the one of them vppon the other in the crowne of this realme, or clayme or chalenge your ſaid imperiall crowne in any other fourme or degree of diſcente or ſucceſſion then is afore lymytted by this act: Or if any perſon or perſons, to whom it ſhal pleaſe your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your mooſte excellent goodnes, by auctoritie of this acte to giue and diſpoſe your ſaid crowne and dignitie of this realme, or the heires of any of them, do at any time hereafter demaunde chalenge or clayme your ſaide crowne of this realme, other wyſe or in any other courſe fourme degree or condition, then the ſame ſhall be giuen diſpoſed and limitted vnto them by your highnes, by vertue and auctoritie of this acte. Or if any ſuch perſone or perſones, to whom your maieſtie ſhal hereafter giue or diſpoſe your ſaid crowne by auctoritie of this acte, or any of their heires, do interrupte or let any of the heires of your maieſtie, that is or ſhalbe begoten, borne, &amp; procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated vnder your laufull pure ſincere and vndouted mariage nowe had and ſolempniſed betwene your highnes and your ſaid moſte dere and entierly beloued wife quene Iane, or any other your laufull heyres here after to be begoten of your body by any other laufull mariage, peaſably &amp; quietly to kepe haue and enioye the ſaide imperiall crowne, and other the premyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by courſe of inheritaunce according to the limitation therof, expreſſed and declared by this acte, that then all &amp; ſingular the offendours in any of the premiſſes contrary to this acte,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> &amp; all their abbetours mainteinours fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours counſaylours and aydours therin, ſhalbe demed and adiudged high traytours to the realme. And that euery ſuch offence ſhall be accepted repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and taken to be high treaſon, and the offendours therin, their aidours maynteinours fautours conſaylours and abettours and euery of them, for euery ſuch offence ſhal ſuffre ſuch iudgement and peines of death, loſſes &amp; forfaitures of landes goodes and priuileges of ſainctuary, as in any caſes of highe treaſon. And ouer that as well your ſayde heires and children, as euery ſuch perſon and perſons, to whom your highneſſe ſhall limitte youre ſaid crowne, in fourme as is aforeſaide, and euery of theyr heyres for euery ſuche offence aboue ſpecified, by them or any of them, to be committed, ſhal loſe and forfaite as well all ſuche righte title and intereſte, that they maye
<pb facs="tcp:150869:13"/> clayme or challenge in or to the crowne of this realme, as heires by diſcent, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by reaſon of any gifte or act that ſhalbe done by your highnes, for his or their aduauncement, by auctoritie of this acte, or other wyſe by any maner of meanes or pretence what ſo euer it be.</p>
            <p>¶And be it further enacted by auctoritie aforeſaide, that if any perſon or perſons, of what aſtate degree dignitie or condition ſo euer they be, at any <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hereafter, by wordes writinge imprintinge, or by any exterior acte or dede, maliciouſly or willingly procure, or do or cauſe to be procured or done directly or indirectly, any thinge or thinges, to the perill of your moſte roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon, or to the perill of the perſon of any your heires or ſucceſſours ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng the royall eſtate of the crowne of this realme: or maliciouſly or wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly giue occaſion by wordes writing print deede or acte, wherby youre highnes or any your ſaide heires or ſucceſſours, hauyng the royall eſtate of the crown of this realme, might be diſturbed or interrupted of the crown of this realme: Or by wordes writing print dede or act procure or do, or cauſe to be procured or done any thing or thinges, to or for the interruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repele or adnullation of this acte, or of any thing therin conteined, or of any thing that ſhall be done by your highnes in the limittation and diſpotion of your crowne by auctoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Or by wordes writing print dede or act pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure or cauſe to be procured or done any thing or thinges, to the preiudice ſclander diſturbance or derogation of the ſaid laufull matrimony, ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſed betwene your maieſtie and the ſaid quene Iane, or any other your lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful wife or wiues hereafter by your highnes to be taken: Or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peril ſclan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der or diſheriſon of any of the iſſues and heires of your highnes, being ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by this acte to enherite, and to be inheritable to the crown of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, in ſuch forme as is aforeſaid: Or to the interruption or diſheriſon of any ſuch perſon or perſons, to whom your highnes ſhal aſſigne and diſpoſe your ſaid imperiall crowne by auctoritie of this act, as is afore remembred: wherby any ſuch iſſues or heires of your highnes, or ſuch other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, might be diſtroied diſturbed or interrupted in fame body or title of the inheritance to the crowne of this realme, as to them is limitted in this act, informe aboue reherſed, or as to them ſhalbe limitted and aſſigned by your highnes, by vertue &amp; auctoritie of this acte. Or if any perſon or perſons by wordes writinge imprinting or any other exteriour acte directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepte or take, iudge or beleue any of the mariages had &amp; ſolempniſed betwene the kinges highnes and the ſaid lady Katharine, or betwene the kinges highneſſe and the ſaid late quene Anne, to be good lauful or of any effect. Or by wordes writing printinge or any other exterior acte directly or indirectly, ſclander interrupte empeche gaynſaye or impugne the lawefull iudgementes and ſentences of the ſaid moſt reuerende father in god, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas archebiſhop of Canturbury and primate of all England, for and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the deuorces and ſeparations of the ſaide vnlaufull maryages or any of them. Or by wordes writinge print or any other exterior acte directly or indirectly, take, accepte, name, or cal by any pretence any of the children
<pb facs="tcp:150869:14"/> borne and procreated vnder any of the ſaide vnlauful mariages, to be legit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and lauful children of your maieſty. Or if any perſon or perſons craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely ymagine inuente or attempt by colour of any pretence to depriue the kinges highnes, the quene, or the heires of their bodies begotten, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the heires of the kinges body laufully begotten, or any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to whom the kinges highnes ſhall diſpoſe giue and limit the crowne of this realme, by auctoritie of this acte, of any of their titles ſtiles names degrees or royal eſtates or regall power. Or if any perſon or perſons at any time hereafter, being required or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by the kinges highnes, or by ſuch perſon or perſons, as ſhalbe auctoriſed by his grace or his laufull hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to make or take an othe, to anſwere to ſuch queſtions and interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as ſhalbe obiected to them, vpon any clauſe, article, ſentence or worde, conteined in this acte, do contemptuouſly or vtterly refuſe to make or take ſuch oth, or without fruſtratorie delay do not make or take the ſame oth: or after the making or taking ſuch othe, do contemptuouſly refuſe directly to anſwere to ſuch queſtions and interrogatories, as ſhall be obiected con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the ſame or any part therof: that then euery ſuch perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, of what aſtate degree or condition ſo euer he or they be, and their ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, counſayllours, maynteynours and abettours, and euery of them, for euery ſuch offence afore declared,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> ſhalbe adiudged highe traytours. And that euery ſuch offence afore eſpecified, ſhalbe adiudged high treaſon, and the offendours therin and their aidours counſailours mainteinours and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bettours, and euery of them beinge laufully conuict of any ſuch offence by preſentment verdite confeſſion or proceſſe, according to the cuſtom &amp; lawes of this realme, ſhal ſuffre peynes of deathe, as in caſes of high treaſon. And that alſo euery ſuch offendour, being conuicte as is aforeſaid, ſhal loſe and forfaite to your highnes, and to your heires or ſucceſſours kynges or regal rulers of this realme, all ſuch manours landes tenementes rentes annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and hereditamentes, which they had in poſſeſſion as owners, or were ſole ſeaſed of by or in any right title or meanes, or any other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had to their vſe of any eſtate of enheritance, at the day of ſuch treaſons &amp; offences by them committed and done. And ſhal alſo loſe &amp; forfaite to your highnes and your ſaid heires, as well all maner ſuche eſtates of freeholde and intereſt for yeres of landes and rentes, as all other goodes cattalles &amp; dettes, which they had at the time of their conuiction or atteinder, of any ſuch offence: Sauynge alway to euery ſuch perſon and perſons and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies politike, to their heires aſſignes and ſucceſſours, and to the heires and ſucceſſours of euery of them (other then ſuch perſons as ſhall be ſo conuicte or atteinted, and their heires and ſucceſſours, and all other clayminge to their vſes) all ſuche righte, title, vſe, intereſt, poſſeſſion, condition, rentes, fees, offices, annuities, and commens, which they or any of them ſhall haue in or vpon any ſuch manours landes tenementes rentes annuities or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, that ſhall ſo happen to be loſt and forfaite by reaſon of any con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiction or atteynder, for any the treaſons &amp; offences aboue reherſed, at any
<pb facs="tcp:150869:14"/> time before the ſaid treaſons and offences committed.</p>
            <p>¶Be it alſo enacted by auctoritie aforſaid, that no perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding in any the treaſons conteined and limitted by this act, or in any other treaſons, ſhal in any wiſe haue and inioy the priuilege or immunitie of any maner ſainctuarie within this realme, or els where, within any the kinges dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but ſhal vtterly loſe, and be excluded of the ſame: any vſe, grant,<note place="margin">Sainctuary.</note> cuſtome, preſcription, confirmation, or any other thinge or thinges to the contrary hereof in any wiſe not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶And be it alſo enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid, that if your maieſtie ſhall happen to deceaſſe before any ſuch your iſſue and heire male of your body, which ſhuld inherite the crowne of this realme, ſhalbe of his age of .xviii. yeres, or before that ſuche your iſſue and heire female, whiche ſhulde inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the crowne of this realme, ſhalbe maried, or be of the age of .xvi. yeres, whiche almyghty god defend) that than the ſaid iſſue and heire male to the crowne, ſo beinge within the age of .xviii. yeres, or your ſaid iſſue and heire female to the crowne, ſo beinge vnmaried, or within the ſaid age of .xvi. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſhall be and remayne, vntyll ſuche time as ſuch iſſues and heyres ſhall come to their ſaid ſeuerall ages afore limitted, at and in the gouernance of their naturall mother, and of ſuche other your counſaylours and nobles of your realme, as your highnes ſhall limitte and appoynt by your laſte wyll made in writynge, ſygned with your mooſte gracyous hande, yf it ſhall be thought by your highnes moſte conuenyent ſoo to be: or elles the ſayd yſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues and heyres ſhall be at and in the gouernaunce of ſuche of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylours and nobles of youre realme, as your maieſtie ſhall name and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt by your laſt wyll made in writynge, and ſigned with your moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous hande, as is aforeſaide. And if any perſon or perſons, by wrytynge,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> printing, or exterior dede or act, directly or indirectly, procure or do, or cauſe to be procured or done, any thinge or thinges, to the lette or diſtourbance of the ſame: that than euery ſuch offence ſhall be high treaſon, and the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours beinge therof conuicted, ſhall ſuffre ſuch peynes of deathe and loſſe of inheritaunce, priuileges of ſainctuaries, freeholdes, intereſtes for yeres, goodes, cattalles, and dettes, in ſuch maner and fourme as is aboue ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in caſes of treaſon afore mencioned.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND</hi> for the more ſure eſtabliſhment of the ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your moſt roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all maieſtie, accordinge to the tenour and fourme of this acte, Be it further enacted by auctorytie aforeſayde, that as welle all the nobles of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme ſpirituall and temporall, as all other your ſubiectes nowe liuing and beinge, or that hereafter ſhall be at their full ages, by the commaundement of your maieſtie, or of your heires or ſucceſſours,<note place="margin">Othe.</note> at al times hereafter from time to time wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhal pleaſe your highnes, or your heires or ſucceſſours to apoynt, ſhal make a corporal othe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of your highnes, or your heires or ſucceſſours, or before ſuch other as your maieſtie, or your heires or ſucceſſours will aſſigne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, for the kepinge obſeruing defending auowynge and maynteynynge of this acte, and of all thinges that ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:150869:15"/> done by your hyghnes by auctoritie therof, accordinge to the tenour of an othe hereafter enſuinge, That is to ſay: Ye ſhal ſwere, to beare faith truthe and obedience all onely to the kinges maieſtie, ſupreme heed in erthe vnder god of the churche of Englande, durynge his lyfe, and to his heires of his body of his moſt diere and entierly beloued lauful wife quene Iane, bego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and to be begoten and procreated: And further to the heires of our ſaid ſoueraigne lorde, according to the limittation in the ſtatute made for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his ſucceſſion in the crown of this realme, in the parliament begonne and holden at Weſtminſter in the .viii. daye of Iune, in the .xxviii. yere of the kinges moſt gratious reigne. And alſo for lacke of ſuch heires, to ſuch perſon &amp; perſons as the kinges highnes ſhall limitte and appoint to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown, by vertue &amp; auctoritie of the ſame act, and not to any other within this realm, nor foreine auctoritie power or potentate. And in caſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other othe be made, or hath be made by you to any perſon or perſons: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then ye to repute the ſame as vayne &amp; adnichilate. And that to your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge writte and vttermooſte of your power, without gyle, fraude, or other vndewe maner, ye ſhall obſerue kepe maynteine and defende the ſaide acte of ſucceſſion made in the ſaide parliament, begon and holden at weſtmyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the ſaid .viii. day of Iune, in the ſaide .xxviii. yere of the kinges moſt roiall reigne, and al the holle effectes and contentes therof, and al thinges that ſhall be done by the kinges highnes by auctoritie of the ſame, and all other actes and ſtatutes made in confirmation or for executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, or of any thing therin conteined: and this ye ſhal do againſt al maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of what eſtate dignitie degree or condition ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer they be: &amp; in no wiſe do or attempte, nor to your power ſuffre to be done or attempted directlie or indirectly any thing or thinges priuily or appertely, to the let hinderaunce damage or derogation therof, or of any parte of the ſame, or of any thynge or thinges, that ſhal be done by the kinges highneſſe, by vertue or auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſaid act, by any maner of meanes, or for any maner of pretence, ſo helpe you god, al ſaintes, and the holy Euangeliſtis.</p>
            <p>¶And it is alſo enacted by auctoritie afore ſaide, that all maner your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, as well ſpirytuall as temporall, ſuynge lyuerey, or ouſter le mayne, out of the handes of your highneſſe, or of your heires or ſucceſſours, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge any feyltie to your highneſſe, or to your heires or ſucceſſours, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of tenure of theyr landes, ſhall ſwere the ſaide corporall Othe aboue mencyoned. And that they nor any of theym, ſhall here after haue any ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereys, ouſtre le mayne, or reſtytution out of your handes, nor oute of the handes of your heyres or ſucceſſours, tylle they ſhall haue made the ſaide corporall Othe, in fourme aboue reherſed. And if any perſon or perſones, beynge commaunded by auctorytye of this acte, to make the ſayde Othe afore lymytted, obſtynately or wylfullye refuſe that to doo, or wyll proteſte and ſaye, whan they ſhall be examyned vpon any interrogatories, that ſhal be obiected to theym, for or concernynge this acte, or any thyng therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:15"/> that they be not bounde to declare their thought and conſcience, and ſtyffely theron abyde: that then euery ſuche perſonne ſoo doynge, for euery ſuche offence ſhall be taken and accepted for offendour in hyghe treaſon.</p>
            <p>And that euery ſuche refuſell ſhall be demed and adiudged highe treaſon,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> and the offendour therin, beinge as afore is limitted, lawefullye conuicted or attemted therof, by the lawes of this realme, ſhall ſuffre ſuche peines of death loſſes and forfaitures, and alſo loſe priuileges of ſaintuaries, in like maner and fourme as is aboue mentioned, for the treaſons afore limitted by this acte.</p>
            <p>¶And be it further enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliamente, that if it ſhall pleaſe the kynges maieſtie at any tyme here after, by his letters patentes vnder his greate ſeale, or by his laſte wyll made in wrytinge,<note place="margin">Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</note> and ligned with his moſt gratious hande, to auaunce any perſon or perſons of his moſt royall bloud to any title ſtyle or name, of any eſtate dignitie or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, what ſo euer it be, and to gyue to them or to any of them any caſtelles honours manours landes teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes liberties fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſes, or other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, in fee ſymple fee tayle or for terme of theyr lyues, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life of any of them: that then al and euery ſuch letters patentes and laſt wyl of his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo to be made to any ſuch perſon or perſones of his blode, ſhal be good and effectuall to them and euery of them, according to the tenour purpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and effectes of euerye ſuch letters patentes and laſte will. And that the ſaid perſone and perſones, and euery of them, ſhall haue and enioy as well all ſuche titles ſtyle and names of honour dignitie and eſtate, whiche ſhall be conteyned, and expreſſed in any ſuch letters patentes or laſte wyll of the kynges hyghnes, as ſuche caſtelles honours manours landes tenementes lyberties francheſes, and all other hereditamentes, whiche ſhall be ſpecify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and mencyoned in euery ſuch letters patentes or laſt will in ſuch maner fourme fation and condicion, and according to ſuch eſtate or eſtates in the lawe, as ſhalbe expreſſed and limitted in euery ſuche letters patentes or laſt wyll, in as large and ample maner, to all intentes and purpoſes, as if the titles ſtyles and names of honour dygnitie and eſtate, and the caſtelles ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours manours landes tenementes lyberties francheſes and other heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes, whiche ſhall be compryſed in any ſuch letters patentes or laſte wyll to be made, were all redye yeuen by good &amp; ſufficient letters patentes to ſuche perſonne or perſons, of the kynges blode by theyr ſpeciall names and ſurnames, and ratyfyed and confyrmed by auctoritie of this preſente parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. Or as if the names of ſuche perſonne and perſonnes, ſoo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of the kinges bloudde, and ſuch titles ſtiles names caſtelles honours manours landes tenementes lyberties francheſes or other hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, hadde ben ſpecyally named and expreſſed in this acte, and gyuen to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perſon and perſonnes of the kinges bloude by theyr propre names and ſurnames, by ſufficient wordes termes clauſes &amp; ſentences, immediatly by auctoritie of this preſent parliament. Sauinge to al and euery perſon and perſons and bodyes politike, and to theyr heyres aſſignes and ſucceſſours
<pb facs="tcp:150869:16"/> other than to the kinges highnes, his heyres or ſucceſſours, al ſuch ryghte title intereſt poſſeſſion rentes annulties fees offices comens rightes intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes petitions condicions, &amp; all other hereditamentes, which they or any of them may or mought claime of in or to any the ſaid titles ſtiles names, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles honours manours landes tenementes liberties fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſes and other heredytamentes conteyned or mentioned in any ſuche letters patentes or laſte wyll, in as large and ample maner, as if this acte hadde neuer be had nor made.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND BE</hi> it fynally enacted by auctoritie afore ſaid, that this preſente acte, and euery clauſe article and ſentence compriſed in the ſame ſhal be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and accepted, according to the plaine wordes and ſentences therin con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined, and ſhall not be interpreted nor expounded by colour of any prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe or cauſe, or by any ſubtill argumentes inuentions or reaſons, to the hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance diſturbance or derogation of this act, or any part therof: Any thing or thinges acte or actes of parlyament here to fore made, or here after to be had done or made to the contrary therof not withſtanding. And that euery acte ſtatute lawe prouiſion thinge and thinges heretofore had or made, or here after to be hadde done or made, contrary to the effecte of this ſtatute, ſhall be voyde and of no value nor force.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for continuaunce of the ſtatutes againſte the caryage of braſſe latenne and coper out of this realme, And for making of cables and ropes: for the wyndynge of wolles, &amp; agaynſt kyllynge of weynelynges vnder the age of two yeres. Cap. viii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the laſte parlyamente begonne and holden at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the thyrde daye of Nouember, in the .xxi. yere of the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges moſt gratious reigne, &amp; frome thens adiorned to weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, and there holden and continued by diuers proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vntyl the diſſolution therof, it was ordeined and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed amongeſt other thinges one acte for reſtrayning the caryages of braſſe,<note place="margin">Braſſe, laten and copper.</note> latten, and coper out of this realme: And alſo one other acte was made in this parliament for the trewe makinge of cables halſers and ropes:<note place="margin">Cables, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers ropes. wynding of wolles. Kyllynge of weinlynges.</note> One other acte for the trewe windinge of wolles: and one other act to reſtraine killing of weinelinges bullockes ſteres or heſter, being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the age of two yeres. All whiche foure ſeuerall actes were made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and endure to the nexte parliament, as by the ſaid actes more plainly appereth. For as moch as the ſaid ſeuerall actes, and euery of them, be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the common welth of this realm, be it therfore enacted by aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this preſente parliament, that the ſaid foure ſeuerall actes, and all clauſes articles and prouiſions therin conteyned, ſhall from henſforthe be and ſtande good and effectuall, and to endure and contynue vntyll the laſte daye of the nexte parlyament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:16"/>
            <head>¶In act for continuance of the ſtatutes of petiurie, for making of iayles, for pewteres, and for ſowynge of flaxe and hempe. Cap. ix.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begonne and holden at London the thirde day of Nouembre, &amp; from thenſe adiourned to weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, and there holden and continued by prorogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the .xv. day of Ianuarie, in the .xxiii. yere of the reigne of our moſte dradde ſoueraigne lorde kynge Henry the .viii.<note place="margin">Atteynt. Periury. Iayle.</note> it was then in that ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaid parliament one act made and eſtabliſhed for the atteintes to be ſued for puniſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of periurye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vntrue verdictes, which acte was then made to endure to the laſt daye of the nexte parliament. And where alſo in the ſaide ſeſſion of the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament one acte was made and eſtabliſhed, for making of iayles in diuers ſhires of this realme, whiche acte was than made to continue and endure for one yere nexte after the ende of the ſame parliament. And where alſo in the time of the ſame parliament,<note place="margin">Pewterers</note> one other acte was made concerning pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, which act was alſo made to endure to the laſt day of the next parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And alſo in the time of the ſaid parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t one other acte was made concerning ſowinge of flaxe and hempe,<note place="margin">Flax and hemp.</note> which acte alſo was made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and indure to the laſt day of th nexte parliament, as by the ſaid foure ſeuerall actes more plainely appereth. For as moch as the ſaid foure actes be good and beneficiall for the common welth of this realme, be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſente parliament, that the ſaid foure actes, and euery of them, and al clauſes articles and prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therin conteined, ſhall ſtande continue and endure in theyr force and ſtrengthe, and be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kepte to the laſte day of the nexte parliamente.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte extinguiſhing the auctoritie of the biſhop of Rome. Ca. x.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moch as not withſtanding the good &amp; holſome lawes ordinances and ſtatutes heretofore made enacted &amp; eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the kinges highnes our moſte gratious ſoueraigne lord, and by the hole conſent of his high courte of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the extirpation abolution and extinguiſſment out of this realme, &amp; other his graces dominions ſeignories and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis, of the pretended power and vſurped auctoritie of the biſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Byſhope of Rome.</note> by ſome called the pope, vſed within the ſame or elles where, concerninge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame realme dominions ſegniories or countreis, which dyd obfuſcate and wreſte goddes holy worde and teſtament a longe ſeaſon from the ſpiritual and trewe meanynge therof, to his worldelye and carnall affectyons, as pompe, glorye, auaryce, ambytion, and tyrannye, couerynge and ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the ſame, with his humayne and polytike deuiſes, traditions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, ſette forthe to promote and ſtablyſhe his onelye domynion, bothe vppon the ſowles and alſo the bodyes and goodes of all Chriſtyan people
<pb facs="tcp:150869:17"/> excluding Chriſt out of his kingedome and rule of man his ſoule, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as he may, and all other temporall kinges and princes out of theyr do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which they ought to haue by goddis lawe, vppon the bodies and goodes of theyr ſubiectes: wherby he dyd not onely robbe the kinges maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, being onely the ſupreme head of this his realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnder god, of his honour, righte, and preemynence, due vnto hym by the lawe of god, but ſpoiled this his realme yerely of innumerable treaſure, &amp; with the loſſe of the ſame, deceiued the kinges louing &amp; obedient ſubiectes, perſwadinge to them by his lawes, bulles, and other his deceiuable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſuche dreames, vanities, and fantaſies, as by the ſame many of them were ſeduced and conueied vnto ſuperſtitious and erronious opinions: ſo that the kynges maieſtie, the lordes ſpirytuall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this realme being ouerweried and fatigated, with thexperience of the infinite abhominations and miſchefes procedinge of his impoſtures, &amp; craftilie colouring of his deceites, to the great damages of ſoules bodyes and goodes, were forced of neceſſitie for the publique weale of this realme, to exclude that forein pretended power iurisdiction and auctoritie, vſed &amp; vſurped within this realme, and to deuyſe ſuch remedies for theyr relife in the ſame, as doth not onely redounde to the honour of god, the highe praiſe and aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the kinges maieſtie, and of his realme, but alſo to the great and ineſtimable vtilitie of the ſame. And not withſtandinge the ſaid holſome lawes ſo made, and heretofore eſtabliſſhed, yet it is commen to the knowlege of the kinges highnes, and alſo to diuers and many his louing faithfull and obedient ſubiectes, howe that diuers ſedicious and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſones, being impes of the ſaide biſſhoppe of Rome and his ſee, and in harte, membres of his pretended monarchy, do in corners &amp; elles where, as they dare, whiſper inculke preache and perſwade, and from time to time inſtill in to the eares and heades of the pore ſimple and vnlettered people, the aduauncement and continuaunce of the ſaid biſhoppes feined and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended auctoritie, pretending the ſame to haue his grounde and original of goddes law, wherby the opinions of many be ſuſpended, theyr iugementes corrupted &amp; deceiued, and diuerſitie in opinions augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; encreaſed, to the great diſpleaſure of almighty god, the high diſcontentation of our ſaid moſt dred ſouerain lord, and the interruption of the vnitie loue charite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that ought to be in a chriſten region and congregation. For auoydynge wherof and repreſſion of the folyes of ſuche ſedicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as be the meanes and authors of ſuch inconueniences, Be it enacted ordeyned and eſtabliſhed by the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſente parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling demurring inhabiting or reſiant within this realme, or within any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kinges dominions ſeignouries or countreis, or the marches of the ſame, or els where within or vnder his obeiſance and power of what eſtate dygnitie preeminence order degre or condition ſo euer he or they be, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:17"/> laſte day of Iuly, which ſhal be in the yere of our lord god .M.D.xxxvi. ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writinge cifring printing preching or teching, dede or acte obſtinately or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aliciouſely holde or ſtand with, to extoll ſetforth maynteyne or defend the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctoritie iurisdiction or power of the biſſhop of Rome, or of his ſee, hereto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> claymed vſed or vſurped within this realme or in any dominion or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye beynge of within or vnder the kynges power or obeyſaunce, or by any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tence obſtinately or maliciouſely inuent any thinge for thextollynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cement ſettyng forth mainteinance or defence of the ſame, or any part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of, or by any pretence obſtinately or maliciouſely attribute any maner of iurisdiction auctoritie or preeminence to the ſaid ſee of Rome, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> biſhop of the ſame ſee for the time beyng, within this realme or in any the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges dominions or countreyes: that then euery ſuch perſon or perſonnes ſo doynge or offendinge, their aydoues, aſſiſtentes, comforters, abbettours, procurers, maynteyners, fautours, counſaylours, concelours, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being therof laufully conuicted, according to the lawes of this realme, for euery ſuch defaulte and offence ſhall incurre and runne in to the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers penalties peines and forfaitures ordeyned and prouided by the ſtatute of prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and premunire, made in the .xvi. yere of the reigne of the noble &amp; valiaunt prince king Richarde the ſeconde, ayenſt ſuche as attempte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure or make prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſee of Rome or els where, for any thing or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the derogation or contrary to the prerogatiue royall or iurisdiction of the crowne and dignitie of this realme.</p>
            <p>¶And to the entente that this acte at all tymes may be wel and trewly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, and the offendoues therof haue and receyue condigne puniſhement according to their demerites, It is enacted by the auctoritie afore ſayde, that as well iuſtyces of aſſiſe in their circuites,<note place="margin">Iuſtices of aſſyſe and peace.</note> as iuſtyces of peace within the limittes of their commiſſion and auctorities, or two of euery ſuch iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciers of peace at the leaſt, wherof one to be of the quorum, ſhall haue ful po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and auctoritie to enquere of all offences contemptes &amp; tranſgreſſions, parpetrated committed or doone contrary to this acte, in like maner and fourme as they may of other offences ayenſt the kinges peace: And ſhall certifie euery preſentment afore them or any of them had or made, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge this acte or any parte therof, before the kinge in his benche, within xl. dayes nexte after any ſuch preſentment had or made, if the terme be then open: And if not, thanne at the firſte day of the terme, nexte folowynge the ſaide .xl. dayes, vpon peyn that euery of the iuſticiers of aſſiſe, or iuſticiers of peace, before whom ſuch preſentment ſhall be made, makynge defaulte of ſuch certificat contrary to this ſtatute, to loſe and forfaite forty poundes to the kynges highnes.</p>
            <p>¶And it is enacted by the auctoritie afore ſayde,<note place="margin">Certificat.</note> that the Iuſticiars of the kinges bench, as well vpon euery ſuch certificat as by enquery before them ſelfes within the limittes of their auctorities, ſhal haue ful power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie to here ordre and determine euery ſuch offence, done or commytted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary this acte, accordinge to the lawes of this realme, in ſuche like maner
<pb facs="tcp:150869:18"/> and fourme to all intentes and purpoſes, as if the perſon or perſons, ayen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom any preſentment ſhalbe had vpon this eſtatute, had be preſented v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon any mater or offence expreſſed in the ſaid eſtatute, made in the ſaid .xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yere of king Richarde the ſeconde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Viſitations.</note>¶ And it is alſo enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaid, that al and euery arc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſhoppes byſhops and archedeacons within this realme, their commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, vycars generall, and other their miniſters, in euery their viſitation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeanes,<note place="margin">Seanes.</note> ſhall make diligent inſearche, enquerie, and examination of al &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery eccleſiaſticall and religious perſonne within and of their iurisdiction, which ſhalbe ſuſpected accuſed or demed to be a tranſgreſſour or offendour of this acte. And if vpon ſuch ſerche enquirie and examination any eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall or religious perſons ſhall be preſented ſuſpected accuſed, or founde culpable by witnes or confeſſion, of any offence contrary to this acte, and be preſente at the time of ſuch preſentmente examination or accuſation: that then euery the archbiſſhoppes biſhoppes and archedeacons, their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, vicars general, and other their miniſters, afore or to whom any ſuch perſonne ſhalbe preſented ſuſpected accuſed or founde culpable (as is afore ſaide) ſhall committe euery ſuche perſone ſo preſented ſuſpected accuſed or founde coulpable, if he be preſente (as is aforeſaid) to the next common iaile of the ſhyere, where ſuch enquitie examination or accuſation ſhalbe had or made, or elles by good &amp; ſufficient ſureties, to be bounden by obligation to the kinges vſe, ſhall lette euery ſuch perſonne to bayle by their diſcretions, to appere before the kinge and his counſaile in the ſterre chaumbre at weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynſter, within .xv. dayes nexte after ſuche enquirie preſentment or accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the terme be then open and kepte, or elles in the firſt day of the terme nexte folowynge after the ſame enquerie preſentment or accuſation. And at the ſame day lymitted for ſuch apparaunce, they ſhall certifie in to the ſaide ſterre chamber by writinge vnder their ſeales, as well the ſaide bonde and obligation taken for ſuch apparance, as the preſentment examination ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation or conuiction of euery ſuch perſonne, and all depoſytions and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces therof, and the name of the iayle, where vnto they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſaide perſonne. And if any ſuche eccleſiaſticall or religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, beinge preſented ſuſpected or accuſed in any ſeane or viſitation, be not preſent at the tyme of the ſaid ſeane or viſitation, as is afore ſaid, that then neuer the leſſe euery the ſaid archebiſſhoppes biſhoppes and archedeacons, their commiſſaries, vicars generall, and all other their miniſters, afore or to whom any ſuche preſentement ſuſpection or accuſation ſhalbe had or made, ſhall certifie euery ſuch preſentement ſuſpection and accuſation, and al cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance therof (as is afore ſaid) in to the ſterre chaumbre at weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in .xv. dayes nexte after ſuche preſentment ſuſpection or accuſation had or made, or in the firſt day of the terme next folowinge after ſuch preſentment ſuſpection or accuſation, in ſuch maner &amp; fourme as is afore reherſed. And in caſe any eccleſiaſticall or religious perſon, being preſented ſuſpected or accuſed of any offence done or attempted contrary to this eſtatute, be therof
<pb facs="tcp:150869:18"/> conuicted by confeſſion or witnes before any archebiſſhoppe biſſhop or arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, or before any the commiſſaries, vycars general, or other their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in their ſeanes or viſitations, or before the kynges counſayle in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chaumbre at weſtminſter: that then euery ſuch ſpirituall and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon, ſo being conuicte, ſhal ſuffre ſuche peynes penalties and forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, as be expreſſed in the ſaid ſtatute made in the ſaide .xvi. yere of kinge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>harde the ſeconde.</p>
            <p>¶It is alſo enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaide,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtical Iuge.</note> that if any eccleſiaſticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge or viſitatour, do voluntarily concele cloke hyde or colour any preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accuſation or confeſſion,<note place="margin">Viſitour.</note> that ſhalbe made to hym concerning this ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and do not certifie euery ſuch accuſation preſentment or confeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the kinge and his counſayle in the ſterred chaumbre at weſtminſter, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch maner and fourme as is aboue ſpecified in this eſtatute: that then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry ſuch eccleſiaſticall iudge and viſitatour, ſo wilfully offendynge, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry ſuch default ſhal forfaite .xl. li. the one halfe therof to the kinges high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, the other halfe to ſuch perſon as will ſue for the ſame by original wryt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> plainte or information in any of the kinges courtes, in whiche ſuite no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yne protection or wager of lawe ſhall be admitted nor allowed.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND FOR</hi> ſtronger defence and mainteynaunce of this acte, it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and enacted by auctoritie afore ſaide, that all and euery eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call iudge, ordynary, chauncellour, commiſſarye, offycyall, vycar generall, and other eccleſiaſticall officer or miniſter, of what dignitie preeminence or degree ſoo euer they ſhall be. And all and euery temporall iudge, iuſticyar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yer, bayliffe, ſhereffe, vnderſhereue, eſchetour, alderman, iurate, conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hedborowe, Thyrdborow, borſolder, and euery other laye officer and miniſter, to be made created elected or admitted within this realme or any other the kinges domynyons, of what eſtate ordre degree or condition ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſhalbe, from and after the ſaide laſt daye of Iuly, ſhal before he take vpon him the execution of ſuche office,<note place="margin">Othe.</note> make take and receyue a corporall othe vpon the Euangelyſtes, before ſuch perſon or perſones, as haue or ſhal haue auctoritie to admit him, that he from henſforth ſhall vtterly renounce refuſe relynquiſſhe or forſake the biſhop of Rome, and his auctoritie power and iurisdiction: And that he ſhal neuer conſent nor agree, that the biſſhop of Rome ſhal practiſe exerciſe or haue any maner of auctoritie iurisdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or power within this realme, or any other the kinges dominions, but that he ſhall reſiſte the ſame at all times to the vttermooſte of his power.<note place="margin">Supreame heade of the Churche of Englande.</note> And that from hensforth he ſhall accepte repute and take the kynges maieſtie to be the onely ſupreme hedde in erthe of the church of England. And that to his cunninge wytte and vttermooſte of his power, without gyle fraude or other vndew meane, he ſhall obſerue kepe maynteyne and defende the holle effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and contentes of all and ſynguler actes and ſtatutes made &amp; to be made within this realme, in derogation extirpation and extynguyſhemente of the biſhoppe of Rome and his auctoritie. And al other actes and ſtatutes made and to be made in reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and corroboration of the kinges power of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb facs="tcp:150869:19"/> hede in earth of the church of Englande: and this he ſhall do ayenſte all maner of perſonnes, of what eſtate dignitie degree or condition they be, and in no wiſe do nor attempt, nor to his power ſuffer to be done or attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted directly or indirectly any thing or thinges pryuely or apartly, to the let hinderaunce damage or derogation therof, or of any part therof, by any ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of meanes, or for any maner of pretence. And in caſe any oth be made or hath bene made by him to any perſon or perſonnes in maynteynaunce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or fauour of the biſſhoppe of Rome or his auctoritie iurisdiction or power he repute the ſame as vayne and adnichilate, ſo helpe him god all ſaintes and the holy Euangeliſte.</p>
            <p>¶And it is alſo enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaide, that all and euerye perſonne and perſonnes ſpirituall and temporall, ſuyng lyuere reſtitutions or vtter le mayne out of the kinge, his heires, or ſucceſſours handes, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge any fealtie to his highnes his heires or ſucceſſours, or whiche ſhall be ſworne to the king his heires or ſucceſſours, or that ſhal haue any office fee or roume of the moſte gratious gifte of the kinges maieſtie, his heyres or ſucceſſours, or ſhall be reteyned in ſeruice with his grace his heires or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, ſhall make take and receyue the ſaide othe. And that alſo all and euery religious perſonne, at the time of his or their profeſſion or entree into religion, and euery other eccleſiaſticall perſonne at the time of his takinge of orders, and all and euery other perſonne, which ſhalbe promoted or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to any degree of lernyng in any vniuerſitie within this realme or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kinges dominions at the time of his promotion or preferment, and euery of them, ſhall make take and receiue the ſaid othe before his or their ſoueraigne, ordinary, or the commiſſarie of ſuch vniuerſitie.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND IT IS ALSO</hi> enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaide, that if any perſonne or perſonnes, lymitted or commaunded by auctoritie of this act to make the ſaide othe, or commaunded by any other perſonne or perſonnes, auctoriſed by the kinges highneſſe commiſſion vnder his greate ſeale, or his ſeale ordeined for cauſes eccleſiaſticall,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> to make the ſaid othe, obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe that to do: that then euery ſuch offence and contempt ſhalbe high treaſon, and the offenders therof being laufully conuicted, ſhall ſuffre pey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death and other forfaitures penalties and loſſes, as is limitted and accuſtomed in caſes of high treaſon by any lawes or ſtatutes of this realme heretofore made.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted, that this acte nor any thing or thinges in the ſame reherſed mentioned or compriſed, be in any wiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicial hurtefull or derogatorie to the ceremonies vſes and other laudable and politike ordinaunces,<note place="margin">Ceremonies.</note> for a tranquilitie, diſcipline, concorde, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, vnitie, and decent ordre heretofore in the church of Englande vſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted taken and accepted, nor to any perſon or perſons accordingly vſing the ſame or any of them.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway and be it enacted by auctoritie of this peſente parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, that this acte, concernynge the byſſhoppe of Rome or any thynge
<pb facs="tcp:150869:19"/> to be done by his vſurped auctoritie, ſhall no further bynde nor extende to and vppon the kinges ſubiectes of his yle of Ierſey, Gerneſey,<note place="margin">Ierſey and Gernſey.</note> and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, in any other maner fourme or condition, than it ſhall pleaſe the kinges highneſſe, with the aduiſe of his mooſte honourable counſayle, vppon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and examination of the ſtate and diſpoſition of his ſaide Iles, and the common welthe of the ſame hereafter to eſtabliſhe, ordeyne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto them by his gratious letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, vnder his great ſeale: And that the ſaid letters patentes and euery thinge therin to be conteyned, ſhall be of the ſame effecte, ſtrengthe, and vertue, as if they had bene paſſed and enacted by auctoritie of parliament, any thinge in the ſaid acte conteyned to the contrary in any wiſe not withſtandinge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte for reſtitution of the firſte fruites in time of vacation to the next Incumbent. Cap. xi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moch as in the ſtatute of the payement vnto the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, his heires and ſucceſſours,<note place="margin">Firſt fruites.</note> of the firſt fruites of ſpirituall promotions, offices, benefyces, and dignities within this realme, and other the kinges dominions, expres mention and declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not had ne made, from what time the yere ſhall be accompted, in which the firſt fruites ſhall be dewe and paiable to his highnes, that is to witte, whether immediately from the dethe reſignation or depriuation of euery incumbente, or from the time of admiſſion or newe takynge of poſſeſſion in euery ſuche promotion. And alſo by reaſon that in the ſame ſtatute it is not declared, who ſhal haue the fruites tithes and other profittes of the ſaide benefices offices promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and dignities ſpirituall, durynge the time of vacation thereof, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of tharchebiſſhoppes and biſhoppes of this realme, haue not onely whan the time of perceiuynge and takynge of tithes, (that is to ſaye, wolle, lambe, corne, and haye, and tithes vſuallye payde at the holye tyme of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) hath approched, differred the collation of ſuche benefices, as haue ben of their owne patronage, but alſo haue vpon preſentations of clerkes made vnto theym by the iuſte patrones, protracted and deferred, to inſtitute, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducte, and admitte the ſame clerkes, to the entente that they myghte haue and perceyue to theyr owne vſe, the ſame tythes growinge, durynge the vacation: Soo that through ſuch delayes (ouer and aboue the firſte fruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, which be iuſtely dewe to the kynges highnes) they haue bene conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo to loſe all, or the moſte part of one yeres profites of their benefices and promotions, and to ſerue the cure at their and their frendes propre co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and charges, or vtterly to forſake and giue ouer their benefyces &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, to theyr greate loſſe and hynderaunce. For reformation wherof, it is ordeyned and enacted by the kinge oure ſoueraigne lorde, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente of the lordes ſpirituall and temporalle, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament aſſembled, and by the auctoritie of the ſame, that the ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:150869:20"/> yere,<note place="margin">Vacation.</note> in whiche the firſte fruites ſhall be payde to the kinges grace, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beginne and be accompted immediately after the auoydaunce or vacatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of any ſuch benefice or promotion ſpirituall afore reherſed. And that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tithes, fruites, oblations, obuentions, emolumentes, commodities, ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntages, rentes, and all other what ſo euer reuenues, caſualties, or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fites certayne and vncertayne, affering or belonginge to any archedeacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, deanry, prebende, perſonage, vicarage, hoſpitalle, wardeyneſhippe, prouoſteſhippe,<note place="margin">Chantries.</note> or other ſpirituall promotion, benefice, dignitie, or office, (chauntries onely excepte) within this realme, or other the kynges dominy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, growinge, ryſinge, or comminge, durynge the time of vacation of the ſame promotion ſpirituall, ſhall belonge and affere to ſuch perſonne, as ſhall be thervnto next preſented, promoted, inſtituted, inducted, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and to his executours, towarde the payment of the firſte fruites, to the kinges highnes, his heires and ſucceſſours: Any vſage, cuſtome, lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, priuilege, or preſcription to the contrary had vſed or beinge in any wiſe notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND IT IS</hi> alſo enacted by thauctoritie aforeſaid, that if any arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſhoppe, biſſhoppe, archedeacon, ordynary, or any other perſonne or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, to their vſes and behoofe, at any tyme heretofore ſythe the firſt daye of May laſte paſte, haue perceyued, receiued, or taken, or at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after do perceyue, receyue, or take the fruites, tythes, obuentions, oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, emolumentes, commodities, reuenues, rentes, aduauntages, profittes or caſualties, commynge, growinge, or belongynge, or whiche hereafter ſhall comme growe affere or belonge to any archedeaconrye, deanrye, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bende, perſonage, vycarage, hoſpitall, wardeyneſhippe, prouoſtſhippe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall promotion, benefyce, dignitie, or office (chauntries onelye excepted) within this realme or other the kinges dominions, durynge the vacation of ſuche archedeaconry, deanry prebende, perſonage, vycarage, hoſpitall, wardeyneſhippe, prouoſteſhippe, or other ſpirituall promotion, benefice, dignitie, or office (chauntries onely excepted) And the ſame vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon reaſonable requeſte from henſforth to be made, doth not render, reſtore, ſatisfie,<note place="margin">Incumbent.</note> contente, and paye to the nexte Incumbent, beynge laufullye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, inducted, or admitted to ſuche archdeaconrye, deanrye, prebende, perſonage, or vycarage, or other promotion, benefice, dignitie, or office ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, excepte before excepted: or do let or interrupte the ſaide Incumbente to haue the ſame: that then euery archebiſſhop, biſhoppe, archedeacon, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie, or other perſon ſo doinge, ſhall forfaite and loſe the treble value of ſo much as he ſhall then haue receyued of the fruites of euery prebend, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, vycarage, hoſpitall, wardeyneſhippe, prouoſteſhippe, or other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall promotion, wherof he ſo ſhall perceyue, receyue, or deteyne, lette, or interrupte the Incumbent, to perceyue, receyue, and haue the fruites, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, obuentions, oblations, emolumentes, commodities, reuenues, rentes, aduantages, profittes, or caſualties: The moytie of whiche forfayture ſhall be to the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the other moytie therof to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent
<pb facs="tcp:150869:20"/> of the ſame prebende, perſonage, or vicarage, or other ſpirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, to be recouered in any of the kinges courtes by action, bylle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nte, information, or other wyſe, in which action or ſuite the defendante <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll not be admitted to wage his lawe, nor any protection or eſſoine ſhal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the defendaunte allowed.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway, that it ſhall be lefull to euery archebiſhop, biſhop, arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>con, and ordinary, their officers and miniſters, to reteine in his or their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>todie, ſo moche of the tithes, fruites, obuentions, oblations, emolumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, commodities, aduauntages, rentes, reuenues, caſualties, and profites, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhall amount to pay vnto ſuch perſon or perſons, as hath or ſhall ſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kepe the cure of ſuche archedeaconry, deanry, prebende, perſonage,<note place="margin">Salary.</note> or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age, or other ſpirituall promotion, durynge the vacation, his or their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſtypende, or ſalarie. And alſo for the collection gathering and leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng of ſuch tythes, fruites, emolumentes, rentes, and other profittes, ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge and growing duryng the vacation aforeſaid: any thing in this acte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alſo, and be it further enacted by the auctoritie aforeſaide, that in caſe any of the incumbentes aforeſaid, happen to dye,<note place="margin">Glebe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</note> and before his death hath cauſed any of his glebe landes to be manured and ſowen at his propre coſtes and charges with any corne or grayne: that then in that caſe all and euery of the ſame incumbentes may make and declare theyr teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of all the profites of the corne, growynge vpon the ſame glebe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſo manured and ſowen: Any thynge conteyned in this preſente acte in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wiſe notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶And where alſo before this tyme diuers and manye perſonnes, vicars, and other ſpirituall perſonnes, beynge ſeaſed, for terme of their lyues, of and in the ſaide ſpirituall promotions afore named,<note place="margin">Leaſes.</note> as well for greate ſommes of money to them before hande paide, as for other cauſes and conſiderations, haue let in ferme for terme of yeres, by ſufficient writinges, their ſaide perſonages, vycarages, and other ſpirituall promotions, or part therof, vnto dyuers and many of the kynges ſubiectes, and after ſuch lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by them ſo made, the leaſſours therof haue often tymes vſed to reſigne their ſaide benefices or ſpirituall promotyons, ſo demyſed and letten in ferme:<note place="margin">Perſonage or vycarage, let to ferme.</note> by reaſon of whiche reſignation and other the actes of the ſaid leaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, the ſaide benefices and other ſpirituall promotions haue ben voide, and the title and intereſtes of the ſaid leaſſes, hath bene therby adnychy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and of none effecte in the lawe, contrary to ryght and good conſcience. For reformation wherof, and for a quietneſſe the better hereafter to be had and contynued betwene the kinges ſubiectes. Be it enacted by auctoritie of this preſente parliament, that from the foreſaide firſte daye of Maye laſte paſſe, no maner of ſuche leaſe, by ſufficient wrytinge heretofore made, nor hereafter to be made by any ſpiritual perſonne within this realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Wales, or the marches of the ſame, to any lay perſonne, of any perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, vycarage, or other ſpirituall promotion aforeſaide within this realme
<pb facs="tcp:150869:21"/> vpon which leaſſe the rent and ſeruices reſerued, with other the yerly char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges of the leaſſe, as in ſeruynge the cure and otherwyſe, ſhall amount with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in fortye ſhillinges by the yere, of as moche as the ſaide perſonage, vyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or other ſpirituall promotion aforeſaide, ſo letten, is rated and vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed at, vpon the kynges bokes, for payinge the firſte fruites, ſhall be adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged voyde adnichilate or determyned, by reaſon of any ſuche reſignation or other auoydance of the ſayd benefice or ſpirituall promotion ſo letten by the onely acte of the ſaide leaſſour, but that euery ſuch leaſſee or grauntee of any ſuch benefices or ſpirituall promotions aforeſayde, their executours or aſſignes, ſhall haue and may enioye their termes and intereſtes of and in the ſame, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme of ſyxe yeres to be accompted next and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the ſaide auoydance, yf the ſaide leaſſour doo ſo long lyue, and the leaſe ſo by him before made, do ſo longe contynue and indure. And that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch auoydaunce, the ſucceſſour or ſucceſſours of euery ſuche leaſſour, ſhall and may diſtreyne for the rent and ſeruices ſo reſerued, and haue their actions of dette and all other aduantages by way of action entre or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, agaynſt the ſaide leſſee, his executours, or aſſignes, for recouerye of the ſaide rent and couenauntes vppon the ſaid leaſe reſerued, as the leſſour therof myghte haue had, if no ſuche auoydance had ben had.</p>
            <p>¶ And further be it enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaide, that if hereafter it happen any ſuch leſſour to deceaſſe and dye before the ende of the terme by hym ſo made, and that there be one yere at leaſte to come of the ſayde terme: that then it ſhall be lawefull to the leſſee therof, his executours or aſſignes, to holde and enioy their ſaid leaſſe to thend of the ſame yere, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he is ſo entered at the time of his ſaide leſſours death, if his ſaide leaſe do ſo longe continewe, bearinge and payenge vnto the ſucceſſoure of euery ſuche leſſour all ſuch rent and ſeruices, as for the remenaunce of the ſayde yere, ſhall vpon euery ſuche leaſe be dewe: for the recouerie wherof the ſaide ſucceſſour ſhall and maye haue all ſuche waies and aduauntages as before is limitted and gyuen to the ſucceſſoure, where his predeceſſour maketh ſuche leaſe and reſygneth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Manſyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage or vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage.</note>¶Prouided alway, that euery ſucceſſour after the deth of his predeceſſour maye and ſhall haue vpon one monethes warnynge after the time of his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duction, the mancyon houſe of euery ſuch perſonage, vicarage, or other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall promotion aforeſaide, with the glebe belonginge to the ſame not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ſowen at the time of his ſaid predeceſſours death, for mayntenaunce of his houſeholde, deductinge therfore in his rent as heretofore hath bene borne for the ſame, or as it is reaſonably worth: any thinge in this ſaid act conteyned to the contrary not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fruites of vacation.</note>¶Prouided alway, that yf the fruites of the vacation of the ſaide ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promotions be not ſufficient to pay the curates ſtypende and wages for ſeruyng the cure the vacation time,<note place="margin">Curate.</note> that then the ſame to be borne and paid by the nexte incumbent within .xiiii. dayes nexte after that he hath the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of any of the ſaide promotions ſpirituall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:21"/>
            <head>¶An acte declarynge the lymittes of the kynges palayce of weſtmynſter. Cap. xii.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR AS MOCHE AS THE KYNGES</hi> palayce at Weſtmynſter, buylded and edyfyed there,<note place="margin">Kynges par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee ſa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce at weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> before the tyme of mynde, by and nygh vnto the monaſterie, and abbey of ſaynt Peter of Weſtmynſter, in the countie of Myddelſex, is and of longe tyme hath ben in vtter ruyne and decaye; And that our moſte drad ſouerayne lorde kynge <hi>HENRY</hi> the eight, kynge of Englande and of Fraunce, defendour of the Faythe, lorde of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and Supreme head in erthe of the Churche of Englande, hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opteyned and pourchaſed one great manſion place and houſe, ſometime parcel of the poſſeſſions and inheritance of the Archebiſhopriche of yorke, ſytuate and beinge in the towne of weſtmynſter, in the ſame countie, not moch diſtaunte from the ſame auncyent Palayce. And the kinges highnes as we of late vppon the ſoyle of the ſaid manſion place, and houſe, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the grounde therevnto adioyninge, moſte ſumptuouſely and curiouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath builded and edified many and diſtincte beautyfulle coſtely and ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte lodgynges, buyldynges, and manſyons, for his gracys ſyngular pleaſure, comforte, and commodytie, to the greatte honour of his hyghnes and of his realme, and thereunto adioyninge hath made a Parke, walled and enuyronned with brycke and ſtone, and therin hath deuyſed and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned many and ſyngular commodious thinges, pleaſures, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, moſt apte and conuenient to appertaine only to ſo noble a prince, for his ſingular comforte, paſtime, and ſolace: Be it therfore enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that all the ſaide ſoyle grounde man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and buyldinges, and the ſayde parke, with all other thynges commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyties and plaſures thervpon made buylded and deuyſed, as is aforeſaid, and alſo the ſoyle of the ſaid auncient palaice, ſhalbe from henſforth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hole palaice at Weſtminſter, and ſo to be taken demed reputed called &amp; named the kinges palaice at weſtminſter for euer. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame palaice ſhall from henſforthe extende and be as well within the ſoyle and places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore limited and appoynted for the ſame, as alſo in all the ſtrete or waye le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge from Charinge Croſſe, vnto the ſeintuarie gate at weſtminſter afore ſaid, and in all the houſes buyldinges landes and tenementes on both the ſides of the ſame ſtrete or way, from the ſaid Croſſe vnto weſtminſter halle, ſituate lyinge or being betwene the water of the Thames of the eaſte part, and the ſaide parke walle of the weſte parte, and ſo forthe throughe all the ſoyle precincte and limittes of the ſaide olde palays.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND THAT</hi> the ſaide palayce nowe made by the auctoritie of this acte, ſhal from henſforth haue and enioy within the precincte, limittes, and boundes before expreſſed and declared of and for the ſame, al ſuch and like prerogatiues, lyberties, preemynences, iurisdyctions, and pryuyleges, as to the kynges aunciente palaice within this realme, haue at any tyme here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb facs="tcp:150869:22"/> belonged vſed or of right apperteined. And that the ſame olde and auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t palace of weſtminſter from henſforth be reputed demed and taken only as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre &amp; parcel of the ſaid newe palaice, made by this act, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: any preſcription recorde or vſage heretofore had vſed or allowed to the contrary notwithſtanding. Sauinge to al and ſingular perſon and perſons, bodies polyke and corporate, theyr heyres and ſucceſſours, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them, al ſuch right title intereſt poſſeſſion rentes reuertion remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre diſtreſſe actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaſe leaſes grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes annuiries ſuites petitions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions in ſuch maner and fourme as they or any of them, their heires and ſucceſſours, or the heires and ſucceſſours of any of them, haue had, ſhulde, myghte, or ought to haue had in the premyſſes or any parcell therof, if this acte had neuer ben had ne made: any thynge in this acte conteyned to the contrary not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alwaies that this preſent act, nor any thing therin conteined, be in any wyſe preiudicyall or hurtfull to Wyllyam Babyngton, keper of oure olde palaice of weſtmynſter, his heires nor aſſignes, for or concerning his ſaid office, but that it ſhall be lefull to the ſaide Wyllyam Babington, his heyres, and aſſignes, to haue holde, occupye, exercyſe, and enioye the ſayde office of keper of the ſayde palaice at weſtmynſter, with all comodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, profytes, aduauntages, and other emolumentes, ryſynge or growinge of the ſame office, in as large and ample maner as if this preſentt acte had not benne made: any thinge in this preſente acte to the contrary heretofore not withſtandynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte compellynge ſpirituall perſons to kepe reſidence vppon their benefices. Cap. xiii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as in the parliament begonne at London, the their day of Nouembre, in the .xxi. yere of the reine of our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne lord king Henry the .viii. and from thens adiorned and proroged to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> palaice of Weſtminſter, the .xvii. daye of Decembre than nexte enſuinge, amongeſt other good actes and ordinances, then and there by the auctoritie of the ſayde parlyament, it was eſtablyſhed, ordeyned, and enacted, that as wel euery ſpiritual perſon, then being promoted to any archdeconry dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or dignitie in any monaſtery or cathedrall churche, or other churche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentual or collegial or being beneficed with any perſonage or vicarage, as al and euery ſpiritual perſon &amp; perſons, which ſhuld after the feaſt of ſaint Mychaell tharchaungell, whiche was in the foreſaide .xxi. yere of the reine of our ſaide ſoueraigne lorde kinge Henry the .viii.<note place="margin">Reſidence.</note> be promoted to any of the ſaid dignities or benefices with any perſonage or vicarage, ſhuld from the ſaide feaſte of ſainte Mychaell tharchaungell, be perſonally reſidente and abydinge at and vpon his ſaid dignitie prebende or benefice or at one of them at the leaſt. And in caſe any ſuch ſpiritual perſon, at any time after
<pb facs="tcp:150869:22"/> the ſaide feaſte, kepte not reſidence at one of his ſaid dignities prebende or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ices (as is afore ſaid) but abſent him ſelfe wilfully by the ſpace of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth together, or by the ſpace of two monethes, to be accompted at ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tymes in any one yere, and make his reſidence and abidinge in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places by ſuch tyme: that then he ſhall forfayte for euery ſuch defaulte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſterlynge, as in the ſame acte more playnely dothe appere. In whiche a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e amonge other prouiſions conteined and ſpecyfyed in the ſame, it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uided, that the ſaid acte of none reſidence ſhulde not in any wiſe extend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be preiuditiall to any ſcholar or ſcholars,<note place="margin">Scholars</note> beinge conuerſaunte and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynge for ſtudye without fraude or couyne at any vnyuerſytie within this realme or withoute, as by the ſame prouyſyon dothe alſo appere more at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge. Sythens the makynge of whiche good acte and ſtatute, dyuers and manye perſonnes, beinge benefyced with cure of ſoule (as is afore ſayde) and beyng not apte to ſtudy, by reaſon of theyr age or other wyſe, ne neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tending before the making of the ſaid act to trauaile in ſtudy within any of the ſaide vniuerſities for the encreaſe of lerninge, but rather mynding &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tending theyr owne eaſe, ſinguler lucre, &amp; pleaſure, by the ſame prouiſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourably to defraude the ſame good ſtatute, &amp; ordinaunce, do dayly &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reſorte and repayre to the ſaid vniuerſities of Oxen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Cambrige and to either of them, where they vnder the ſaid pretence and colour of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doth contynue and abyde, lyuinge diſſolutely, nothing profitinge them ſelfes by ſtudy at all in lerning, but conſume the time in ydelnes, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſtymes and inſolente pleaſures, giuinge occaſion and euylle exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therby to other yonge men and ſtudentes within the ſaid vnyuerſities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tell or nothinge regardinge theyr cure and charge of ſowle, contrarye to the mindes and entente of the makers of the foreſaid good ſtatute &amp; orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. And alſo diuers and many old beneficed men haue &amp; do continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally remayne there, neuer exerciſynge nor practiſynge theyr lerninge, to the example of vertue and mayntenaunce of the common weale, in dyſcharge of their conſcience, according to theyr duetie, hauing neuertheles and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieng ſuch romes and commodities, as were inſtitute and ordeined for the mayntenaunce &amp; reliefe of poore ſcolers, to the great hinderance and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame. Be it therfore enacted by the kinge our ſoueraygne lorde, with the aſſente of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, that all and ſingular ſpirituall perſone and perſones, whiche nowe be or hereafter ſhall be to any benefice or benefices promoted as is aforeſaid, being aboue the age of .xl. yeres, the chancellour, vychancellour, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſary of the ſaid vniuerſities, or any of them, wardens, deanes, prouoſtes, preſidentes, rectours, maſters, principals and other head rulers of colleges, halles, and other houſes or places corporate, within the ſaid vniuerſities, or any of them, doctors of the chaire, reders of diuinitie in the comon ſcholes of diuinitie, in any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid vniuerſities onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhalbe reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; abiding at &amp; vpon one of their ſaid benefices, according to the entent &amp; true meaninge of the ſayd former act, vpon ſuch peyne and
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150869:24"/> penalties as be conteyned in the ſaide former acte,<note place="margin">Benefices perſons.</note> made and apoynted for ſuch beneficed perſons for theyr none reſydence. And that none of the ſaide beneficed perſons, being aboue the age aforeſaid, except before except, ſhall from henſforth be excuſed of theyr none reſidence vpon the ſaide benefices, for that they be ſtudentes or reſiaunt within the ſaid vniuerſities or any of them, any prouiſo, or any other clauſe or ſentence ſpecyfyed or conteyned in the ſaid former acte of none reſidence, or any other thinge or thinges to the contrary hereof in any wyſe not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶And ouer this be it enacted by thauctoritie beforeſaid, that al and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſuch beneficed perſons being vnder the age of .xl. yeres, reſiante and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding within the ſaid vniuerſities, or any of them, ſhall not enioye the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilege &amp; libertie of none reſidence conteined in the prouiſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid former act, made for the ſcholars &amp; ſtudentes of the ſaid vniuerſities or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, onleſſe he or they be preſente at the ordinary lecture and lectures, as well at home in theyr houſes as in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſchole or ſcholes, and in theyr propre perſons kepe ſophemes, problemes, diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and other exerciſes of ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, and be apponente and reſpondent in the ſame, according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and ſtatutes of eyther of the ſaid vniuerſities, where he or they ſhal be ſo abydinge or reſiaunt, any thynge conteyned in the ſaid prouiſo or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acte to the contrary not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway that this acte ſhall begynne to take effecte at the feaſte of ſaynct Mighel tharchaungell nexte comynge, and not before.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway, that this acte, nor any thinge therin conteyned, ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to any perſon or perſons, which nowe is or hereafter ſhall be readers of any publique or common lecture in diuynitie, lawe cyuile, phiſyke, phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,<note place="margin">Reeders of Publique, Lectures.</note> humanitie, or of any of the lyberall ſciences, or publyke or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon interpretours, or techers of the Ebrewtong, Caldey, or Greke, in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer college or place of any of the ſaide vniuerſities the ſaid perſons for the tyme beinge, ſhal rede the ſaide co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon or publique lectures: Nor yet to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon or perſons, which after or about the age of .xl. yeres, which ſhall reſorte to any of the ſaid vniuerſities to procede doctours in diuinitie, lawe ciuile, or phiſike, for the tyme of their ſaide procedinges, and executynge of ſuche ſermons diſpucions or lectures, which they be bound by the ſtatutes of the vniuerſities there to do for the ſayde degrees ſo obteyned.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte lymyttinge the prices of wynes. Cap. xiiii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that no perſon or perſons ſhal ſell any Gaſcoyne Guyon or Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wynes aboue .viii. d. the galon,<note place="margin">Price of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> that is to ſaye, a penye the pynte .ii. d. the quarte .iiii. pence the potel, and .viii. pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the galon, vpon payne of forfaiture for euery pinte to be ſold aboue the ſaid price .iiii. d. and for euery quarte ſold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſayd price .viii. d. and for euery pottel ſo ſolde aboue the ſaid price
<pb facs="tcp:150869:24"/> xii. d. And for euery galon ſo ſolde aboue the ſaide price afore limitted .ii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And that no Malmeſeys, romneys, ſackes, nor other ſwete wynes, ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de by retayle aboue .xii. d. the galo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .vi. d. the potel .iii. d. the quarte, and .i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the pynte, vppon peyne to loſe and forfayte .iii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.iiii. d. for euerye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> .xx. d. for euery potell .xii. d. for euery quarte, and .vi. d. for euery pynte that ſhall be ſolde contrary to this acte.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alwaye, that the lorde Chancellour, lorde Treaſourer, lorde Preſident of the kynges moſt honourable counſayle, lord Priuie ſeale, and the two chiefe Iuſtices of eyther benche, or .v.iiii. or .iii. of them, ſhal haue power and auctoritie by theyr dyſcretyons, to ſette the prices of all kinde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynes, that is to ſaye, of the pryces of the butte, tonne, pype, hogges head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cheon. teers, barrell, or rundelet, when it ſhall be ſolde in groſſe, ſo that they or any of them cauſe the prices by them ſet to be written, and open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation therof to be made in the kynges courte of Chancery openly in the terme tyme, or elles, in the cytie boroughe or towne, where any ſuch wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhall be ſolde in groſſe: any thynge conteyned in this acte to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye hereof not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶And it is further enacted, that if any perſon or perſons, after ſuch prices beſet and put in writinge by the ſaid lord Chauncellour, lord Treaſourer, lorde Preſident of the kinges moſt honorable counſaile, lord Priuie ſeale, and the .ii. chiefe iuſtices, or by .v.iiii. or .iii. of them, and proclamation ther if hadde (as is afore ſaide) do ſell any wines in groſſe by any fraude or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, contrary to the ſaid prices ſo ſette and proclaimed:<note place="margin">wines ſolde in groſſe.</note> that thenne euery offendour in that behalfe ſhall loſe and forfayte for euery veſſelle by them ſolde in groſſe contrary to the ſaid prices .xl.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. the one halfe of al which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faitur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be to the kinge our ſoueraigne lord, and the other halfe ther of, if it be within any cytie borowghe or towne corporate, to be to the mayres, ſhireffes, bailiues, or other head rulers of ſuch cities boroughes or townes corporate. And if it be without citie, boroughe, or towne corporate, then to be to ſuche of the kinges ſubiectes as wyll ſewe for the ſame. And that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuche forfaiture ſhall be recouered by originall writte of det, byll, plaint, or information, In whiche ſuyte no wager of lawe ſhall be admitted, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny protection or eſſoyne allowed.</p>
            <p>¶And it is alſo enacted,<note place="margin">Iuſtices of peace. Head offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> that the Iuſtices of peace in euery ſhyre of this preſent realme, and all maires ſhereues bailyues and other head officers in cyties boroughes and townes corporate, that is to ſaye, euery of them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the limitties of theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions and auctorities, as well within fraunche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as without, ſhal haue power and auctoritie to examine here inquire and determine the defautes of ſuch as ſhal attempte to ſell any wines in groſe or by retayle contrary to this act, and to punyſhe the offendours by impry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment or otherwyſe by theyr diſcretions.</p>
            <p>¶And where as in the parlyament holden at weſtmynſter in the fyrſt yere of the reigne of kinge Rycharde the thyrde,<note place="margin">Tonne of wyne.</note> amonge other thinges it was eſtablyſhed, ordeyned, and enacted, that euery tonne of wine ſhuld conteine
<pb facs="tcp:150869:25"/> CClii. galons, euerye butte of Malmeſey ſhoulde conteyne .Cxxvi. galons, euery pype .Cxxvi. galons, euery tercyan or poncheon .lxxxiiii. galons, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hogges head .lxiii. galons, euery teerce .xli. galons, and euery barrel .xxxi. galons, and di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; euery rondelette .xviii. galons, and di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And that no veſſel ſhulde be putte to ſale, tille it were gauged, vppon peyne of forfayture, as by the ſame ſtatute it doth appere more at large. Neuer the leſſe great dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte is dayely vſed in ſellinge of wines and oyles in caſkes and veſſelles, not bearinge the contentes aboue limitted, to the great loſſe of the kinges poore ſubiectes. For remedye wherof, it is enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that the ſaide eſtatute made in the fyrſte yere of kynge Rycharde the third, and al other eſtatutes heretofore made for trewe gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge and meaſuringe of wines,<note place="margin">Gaugynge of wynes and other licours.</note> oyles, hony, or any other lycours, whiche eſtatutes afore this tyme be not repelled nor expyred, ſhall ſtande in theyr ſtrength and vertue, and be put in due execution, according to theyr tenors and effectes in euery behalfe.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>AND</hi> ouer that be it enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parlyament, that euery gauger within this realme ſhall trewelye and effectually within the limittes of his offyce, gauge all the ſaide tonnes, buttes, pipes, terſes, poncheons,<note place="margin">Gaugeour.</note> tercyans, barrelles, hogges head, and rundlettes, and ſhall playnely and trewly make vppon the head of euerye ſuche veſſell the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the ſame, vppon peine to forfaite to the partie, to whoſe vſe the wine oyle or other thynge therin beinge ſhall be ſold, foure tymes the value of that that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſell ſo marked ſhall lacke of his laufull contente aboue wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: the ſame forfayture to be recouered ouer and beſydes the coſtes of the ſure, by the kinges originall writte, or by byll in any of the kinges courtes of his common lawes, or in any competente courte, hauynge iurisdyciyon in the place, where that offence ſhal be committed, by action or bill of dette, in which action or ſuite, none eſſoyn, protection, nor wager of lawe ſhalbe accepted admitted or allowed to the defendant or defendantes. And that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye marchaunte or other perſonne, ſellinge the ſaide wine, oyle, or other thynge conteyned in the ſaid veſſell marked, ſhall allowe of the price ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the byer of the ſame, for euery quantitie of wine, oyle, or other thynge conteyned in the ſaide marked veſſell, the ful valewe of the lacke therof, beynge by reaſon of defaute of full gauge of the veſſelle, marked, or of defaute of fyllynge of the ſame veſſell, or by reaſon of defaute of any of them, after the rate of the hole price of the wine, oyle, or other thinge, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge ſolde by that veſſell marked: and that vpon peyne of forfayture to the ſame byer the dowble value of the ſame veſſelle and wine, oyle, or other thynge therin beynge ſo ſolde: the ſame forfayture to be recouered to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the coſtes of the ſuyte, in maner and fourme as the forfayture laſte before written is lymytted to be recouered.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:25"/>
            <head>¶An acte for punyſhement of pyrotes and robbers on the ſea. Capit. xv</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here traytours, pirotes, theues, robbers, murtherers,<note place="margin">Pyrates.</note> and confederatours vpon the ſea, many tymes eſcape vnpuniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, bicauſe the triall of their offences hath heretofore ben ordered, iudged, and determined before the Admiral,<note place="margin">Admyrall.</note> or his lieutenaunt or commiſſarie, after the courſe of the ciuile la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, the nature wherof is, that before any iugement of deth canne be yeuen agaynſt the offendours, eyther they muſt playnely confeſſe their offences (which they will neuer do, without torture or peynes) or elles their offences be ſo playnely and directly proued by witneſſe indifferente,<note place="margin">Robbers on the ſea.</note> ſuch as ſawe their offences committed, whiche canne not be gotten, but by chaunce at fewe times, bycauſe ſuch offendours commytte their offences vpon the ſea, and at many times murdre and kylle ſuch perſonnes, beynge in the ſhippe or bote, where they committe their offences, whiche ſhoulde wytneſſe ayenſt them in that behalfe: and alſo ſuche as ſhuld beare witnes be commonlye maryners and ſhipemen, whiche bycauſe of their often vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and paſſages in the ſeas, depart without longe tarienge and protrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, to the great coſtes and charges, as well of the kinges highnes as ſuche as wolde purſue ſuch offendours. For refourmation wherof, be it enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that all treaſons, felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, robberies, murders, and confederacies hereafter to be commited in or vpon the ſea, or in any other hauen riuer, creke, or place, where the admyral or admiralles haue or pretend to haue power auctoritie or iurisdiction, ſhal be inquired tried harde determyned and iudged in ſuch ſhyres &amp; places in the realme, as ſhall be limitted by the kynges commiſſion or comiſſions to be directed for the ſame, in like fourme and condition, as if any ſuch offence or offences had ben committed or done in or vpon the lande, and ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions ſhalbe had vnder the kynges great ſeale, directed to the Admirall or admiralles, or to his or to their lieutenaunt deputie &amp; deputies,<note place="margin">Chancelloure of England,</note> and to iii. or .iiii. ſuch other ſubſtantiall perſones, as ſhall be named or appoynted by the lorde Chauncellour of Englande, for the time beynge, from tyme to tyme, and as ofte as nede ſhall require, to here and determine ſuche offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, after the common courſe of the lawes of this lande, vſed for treaſones, felonies, robberies, murders, and confederacies of the ſame done and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vpon the lande within this realme.</p>
            <p>¶And be it enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaide, that ſuche perſonnes, to whom ſuche commiſſion or commiſſions ſhall be directed, or .iiii. of theym at the leaſt, ſhall haue full power and auctoritie to enquere of ſuch offences and of euery of them, by the othes of twelue good and lauful inhabitantes in the Shire, limitted in their commiſſion: in ſuche like maner and forme, as if ſuche offences hadde benne committed vppon the lande within the ſame Shyre. And that euery inditement founde and preſented before ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:150869:26"/> commiſſioners of any treaſons, felonies, robberies, murders manſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or ſuch other offences, commytted or done, in or vpon the ſeas, or in or vpon any other hauen ryuer or creke, ſhalbe good and effectual in the lawe. And if any perſon or perſons happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be indited for any ſuch offence done or hereafter to be done vpon the ſeas, or in any other places aboue limitted, that then ſuch orders proceſſe iudgement &amp; execution ſhal be vſed had done and made to and agaynſt euery ſuch perſon and perſons, ſo beinge indic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as agaynſte traytours, felons, and murderers, for treaſon, felony, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, murder, or other ſuch offences done vpon the lande, as by the lawes of the realme is accuſtomed. And that the triall of ſuch offence or offences, if it be denyed by the offendour or offendours, ſhalbe had by twelue lauful men, inhabited in the ſhire limitted within ſuch commiſſion, whiche ſhall be directed as is aforeſayde, and no chalenge or chalenges to be had for the hundred.<note place="margin">Challenge.</note> And ſuch as ſhall be conuicte of any ſuch offence or offences, by verdicte confeſſion or proces, by auctoritie of any ſuche commiſſion, ſhall haue and ſuffre ſuche peynes of death, loſſes of landes goodes &amp; cattalles, as if they had ben attaynted and conuicted of any treaſons, felonies, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, or other the ſaid offences, done vpon the landes.</p>
            <p>¶And be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſaide, that for treaſons robberies felonies murders &amp; confederacies, done vpon the ſea or ſeas, or in any place aboue reherſed,<note place="margin">Clergy. Sainctuary.</note> the offendours ſhal not be admitted to haue the benefite of his or their clergie, but be vtterly excluded therof and from the ſame, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo of the priuilege of any ſainctuary.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway, that this acte extende not to be preiudiciall or hurtfull to any perſon or perſons for taking any vittaile, gables, ropes, ankers, or ſayles, whiche any ſuch perſon or perſons (compelled by neceſſitie) taketh of or in any ſhippe, which may conueniently ſpare the ſame, ſo the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone or perſones pay out of hande for the ſame vittaile, gables, ropes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or ſayles money or money worth, to the value of the thinge ſo taken, or to delyuer for the ſame a ſufficient byll obligatorie to be payde in forme folowing,<note place="margin">Straictes of Marrocke.</note> That is to ſay: if the taking of the ſame thinges be on this ſide the ſtraytes of Marroke, then to be paide within .iiii. monethes. And if it be beyonde the ſaide ſtraites of Marroke, then to be payde within .xii. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes next enſuynge the makyng of ſuch billes. And that the makers of ſuche bylles well and truely paye the ſame dette at the daye to be limitted within the ſaid billes.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alwaye, that whanne ſo euer any ſuche commiſſion for the punyſhement of the offences aforeſaide, or of any of them, ſhall be directed or ſent to any place within the iurisdiction of the fyue portes,<note place="margin">Fyue portes.</note> that then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſuch commiſſion ſhall be directed vnto the lorde wardayne of the ſayde portes for the time beinge, or to his deputie, and vnto thre or foure ſuche other perſon or perſons, as the lorde chauncellour for the tyme beynge ſhal name and appoynte: Any thynge in this preſent acte to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtandynge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150869:26"/>
            <p>¶Prouided alway, that whan ſo euer any commiſſion ſhal be directed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fiue portes, for the inquiſition and trialles of any the offences expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this acte, that euery ſuch inquiſition and triall to be hadde by vertue of ſuch commiſſion ſhalbe made and had by the inhabitantes in the ſaide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e portes or the membres of the ſame: any thing in this act to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof not withſtandinge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte for the releaſe of ſuch as haue obteyned pretended lycences and diſpenſations from the ſee of Rome. Capi. xvi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the biſſhoppe of Rome and his predeceſſours,<note place="margin">Byſhoppe of Rome.</note> of his and theyr couetous and ambitious myndes, to thentent to aduaunce and enriche them ſelfes and the ſee of Rome, to the greate em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſſhynge of this realme of Englande, and other the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges domynyons, contrary to goddes lawes, the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, and in derogation of the imperiall crowne of this ſayde realme, haue heretofore wrongefully pretended, extorted, vſed, and exerciſed within the ſame diuers and many vſurped powers, iurisdictions, and auctorities, durynge and by the which tyme the ſayd byſſhoppe and his predeceſſours, arrogantly and iniuſtly haue taken vpon them for great ſummes of money and other profittes to them giuen, to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the kynges ſubiectes, and other inhabitauntes within this realme, and other the kinges dominions, many diuers &amp; ſundry auctorities immunities faculties priuileges lycen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces indulgences and preeminences, of diuers kindes natures and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: which all thoughe they proceded by an iniuſte and vſurped auctory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, haue bene vnto nowe of late by the ſubiectes of this realme temerously and ignorauntly accepted receyued vſed &amp; erronyouſly put in excerciſe and execution: the which vſurped auctoritie iurisdiction and power is nowe iuſtely trulye and ought to be clerely and abſolutely extynguyſhed extirped and abolyſſhed within this realme and other the kynges domynions. And for as moch as all and euery ſuch perſon and perſons bodies polytyke and corporate, which vnlawefully and without any maner of auctoritie or iuſte grounde, heretofore haue temerouſly and ignorantly accepted receyued v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; erroniouſly put in execution and exerciſe the ſaid faculties immunities auctorities priuileges lycences indulgences and preeminences, haue nowe ſincere pure and perfite intelligence and knowlege of the ſaid vſurped auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie iurisdiction and power. And that the ſaid faculties, auctorities, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges, licences, and indulgences, ſo as is aforeſaide accepted receyued v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and erroniouſly exerciſed, were &amp; ben to all intentes and purpoſes clere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly voyde fruſtrate and of none effecte. All be it if they ſhulde be impeached or interrupted of ſuch priuileges liberties preemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces auctorities iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions profittes and other commodities, which they now haue vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe by colour of ſuch vayne and voyde licences diſpenſations and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:27"/> it ſhulde be to their intollerable inquietations and vtter vndoynge. Wherfore be it enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that al bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les breues faculties and diſpenſations,<note place="margin">Bulles. Breues. Faculties. Dyſpenſaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> of what names natures or qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo euer they be of, heretofore had or opteyned of the biſhoppe of Rome, or of any his predeceſſours, or by the auctoritie of the ſee of Rome, by or to any ſubiectes reſiantes or bodies politike or corporate of or in this realme, or of or in any other the kinges dominions, ſhall from henſforth be clerely voyde and of no value force ſtrength nor vertue, and ſhall neuer here after be vſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dmitted allowed pleaded or alleged in any places or courtes of this realme, or of any other the kinges dominions, vpon the peynes contey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in the ſtatute of prouiſion and premunire, made in the .xvi. yere of the reigne of king Richarde the ſeconde. Yet not withſtandinge at the mooſte humble petition and interceſſion of the lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, it maye pleaſe the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, of his moſte gratious benignitie goodnes and bleſſed diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that it maye be enacted by auctoritie of this parliament, that al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages had and ſolempniſed within this realme, or in any other the kinges dominions,<note place="margin">Maryages.</note> before the thirde day of Nouember, in the .xxvi. yere of the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges moſte gratious reigne, wherof there is no deuorce or ſeparation had by the eccleſiaſticall lawes of this realme, &amp; which mariages be not prohibited by goddes lawes, limitted and declared in the act made in this preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament for the eſtabliſhement of the kinges ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or otherwyſe by holy ſcripture, ſhall be by auctoritie of this preſent parliament good laufull and effectual, and ſhalbe from the beginning of ſuch mariages reputed eſtemed taken adiudged receyued approued &amp; allowed by the auctoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament, to al and ſingular purpoſes effectes and ententes, as good as ſufficient and as vayleable, as though no impediment of matrymony had euer ben betwene them that haue contracted and ſolemnyſed ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages: And that all children procreated and to be procreated in and vnder ſuch mariages, ſhall be laufull to all intentes and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Archebiſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes.</note>¶And that it may be alſo enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all archebiſhoppes and biſhoppes of this realme, or of any the kynges dominions conſecrated, and at this preſent time taken and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for archebiſſhops and biſſhops, may by auctoritie of this preſent parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and not by vertue of any prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or other foreyne auctoritie licence facultie or diſpenſation, kepe, enioy, and reteyn their archebiſhoprikes &amp; by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprikes, in as large &amp; ample maner, as if they had ben promoted elected confirmed &amp; conſecrated, according to the dewe courſe of the lawes of this realme. And that euery archebyſhoppe and byſhoppe of this realme, and of other the kinges dominions, may miniſter vſe and exerciſe all and euerye thyng and thinges, perteyning to thoffice or ordre of an archebiſſhop &amp; by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, with al tokens inſignes and ceremonies therunto laufully belonging. And that al eccleſiaſticall perſons of the kinges realme &amp; dominions, which at this time be taken had and reputed for abbottes priours, abbaſſes, prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſes,
<pb facs="tcp:150869:27"/> and other heades of religion (whiche be not nother ſhall be excluded from their dignities by the late acte of ſuppreſſion) and the religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons lyuinge vnder their obedience, and all perſons now taken and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as mayſters preſidentes prouoſtes and wardeynes of cathedrall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and colleges, with the companies and felowſhippes of the ſame, al pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes and clerkes, which haue receyued any of the eccleſiaſticall orders, all archedeacons and deanes, and other hauynge offices cures and dignities ſpirituall, may by auctoritie of this act, and not by the vertue of any forein power or auctoritie, adminiſter vſe and exerciſe all thinges perteininge to their dignities offices ordres cures religions and felowſhippes, and maye laufully hereafter vſe al tokens inſignes, and ceremonies, which they haue ben accuſtomed to vſe in times paſte (ſo it be not expreſly agaynſt the lawes of god and this realme) any thing or thinges conteyned in any act or actes, made ſithen the beginninge of this preſent parliament to the contrary of any the premiſſes in any wiſe not withſtanding.</p>
            <p>¶And where diuers and many of the kinges ſaid ſubiectes haue purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and obteyned many diſpenſations bulles breues and faculties of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome for the tyme beynge, or by auctoritie of the ſee of Rome, as pluralities, vnyons, trialities, appropriations, commendams, exemptions, and other bulles breues and faculties, for diuers cauſes and matters, other than be afore expreſſed, which be of no ſtrength or vertue: it may therfore pleaſe the kynges maieſtie, that it may be enacted by auctoritie afore ſaide, that all and euery his ſaid ſubiectes durynge the time of one hole yere next after the feaſt of ſaincte Michaell the archaungell nexte comminge, maye enioy vſe and haue by auctoritie of this preſent acte, and not by the vertue of the ſaid bulles breues and faculties, al &amp; euery the effectes conteyned &amp; ſpecified in ſuch bulles breues and faculties, in all ſuch caſes onely as may be diſpenſed with by the archebiſhoppe of Canturbury, by auctoritie of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme.</p>
            <p>¶And that it maye be further enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid, that all and euery the kinges ſaid ſubiectes, bryngyng rendrynge and delyuerynge to ſuch perſons of his counſell, or of the maiſters of his chancery, as the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges highnes ſhall name and appoynt, any bulles breues or any other facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerninge any the premiſſes: that then if it ſhall appere to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as the kinges highnes ſhall ſo name and appoynt to receyue ſuch bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les faculties and breues, after dewe examination therof had, that the effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes conteyned and ſpecified in ſuch bulles faculties and breues or any part therof, maye be laufully graunted by the ſaide archebyſhoppe, of Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, by auctoritie of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme: that then &amp; in euery ſuch caſe the kinges ſaide ſubiectes, makinge humble ſuite to haue the effectes conteyned in the ſaid bulles breues and faculties to be granted vnto them,<note place="margin">Chauncellor of Englande.</note> ſhall haue receyue and obteyne of the chauncellour of Englande or keper of the great ſeale for the time beinge, by ſufficient writing in dewe fourme to be made, and to be ſealed vnder the kinges great ſeale, all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:150869:28"/> ſuch effectes conteyned and ſpecified in ſuch bulles breues and fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Archebiſſhop of Cant.</note> as may be laufully graunted by the ſayde archebiſſhoppe of Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bury, by auctoritie of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, paying onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the ſealinge of euery ſuch writinge .xx. ſ .iiii. d. And ouer that for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſonable coſtes for peynes of the writinge therof .iii. ſ iiii. d. and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue, and for the peyne taken for dewe examynation of euery ſuche bulles breues and faculties .iii. ſ .iiii. d. and not aboue. And that this preſent act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhalbe ſufficient and immediate warrant to the chancellour or keper of the greate ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for thenſealing and deliuerie of ſuch licences faculties diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and other writinges, which ſhall be made graunted and ſealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kinges greate ſeale by vertue and auctoritie of this acte.</p>
            <p>¶And it is alſo enacted by auctoritie afore ſayd, that all and euery ſuche lycence diſpenſation facultie confirmation or other writing, to be had made or graunted vnder the kinges great ſeale out of the ſaid court of chauncery by auctoritie of this acte, in fourme as is aboue reherſed, ſhall be good and effectuall to the ſaide parties ſuing for the ſame, according to the tenor and effectes therof, and ſhall be admitted, accepted, and allowed in all courtes and places of this realme, and in all other the kinges dominions: any v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, preſcription, foreyne lawes, cuſtomes, or ordynaunce to the contrary therof notwithſtandinge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte giuinge auctoritie to ſuche as ſhall ſuccede to the crowne of this realme, whan they come to the age of .xxiiii. yeres to make fruſtrate ſuch actes as ſhall be made afore in their time. Capitulo .xvii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moche as lawes and ſtatutes may happen hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be made within this realme, at parlyamentes hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at ſuch time as the kinges of the ſame ſhall happen to be within age, hauynge ſmall knowledge and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their affaires, to the great hynderance and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the imperiall crowne of this realme, and to the vniuerſall damage of the common welthe of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of the ſame, Be it therfore enacted by auctoritie of this preſente par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament, that if the imperiall crowne of this realme, after the deceaſſe of the kynges mooſte royall maieſtie (whoſe lyfe our lorde longe preſerue) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcende, comme, or remayne, to the heires of oure ſaide ſoueraigne lorde, or to any perſone to be limitted by his highnes, as of very right it muſte and ought to do,<note place="margin">Actes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament.</note> according to the lawes of this realme eſtabliſhed for the ſame, the ſaide heires or ſuche perſonne beinge within the age of .xxiiii. yeres, and that then any acte or actes of parliament ſhall happen to be made and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhed in any parliament, that then ſhall be holden, before ſuche heyre or heires perſon or perſones then being in poſſeſſion of the ſaid crowne, ſhall be of their full ages of .xxiiii. yeres: that then euery ſuch heire or heires of
<pb facs="tcp:150869:28"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de ſoueraigne lorde, or ſuch perſone ſo poſſeſſed of the crowne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> within the ſame age of .xxiiii. yeres, ſhall haue full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at all tymes after they ſhall come to theyr ſaide full ages of .xxiiii.<note place="margin">Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by theyr letters patentes, vnder the greatte ſeale of Englande, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, adnulle, and repeale all and ſyngular ſuche actes, made and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by their royall aſſentes in any parlyament holden during the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they were within their ſaide age of .xxiiii. yeres, theyr royall aſſentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de to the ſame, durynge the tyme that they were within the ſaid age of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yeres,<note place="margin">Reuocation of actes.</note> or any acte or actes hereafter to be made to the contrary therof notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶And be it alſo enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid, that euery ſuch repeale ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation and reuocation of any acte or actes, that ſhalbe made and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in any parlyament, holden before the time that ſuch heires or perſon, poſſeſſed of the crowne, ſhall be of the ſaide age of .xxiiii. yeres, ſhall be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and effectuall to al intentes and purpoſes, as though it had ben done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> auctoritie of parlyament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>¶An acte concerning treaſon in certayne caſes. Cap. xviii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that if any man, of what eſtate, degree, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ſo euer he be, at any time hereafter, take vpon him to eſpouſe, mary, or take to his wyfe any of the kynges childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being laufully borne or otherwiſe, commonly reputed or take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his children, or any of the kynges ſyſters or auntes of the part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father or any the laufull childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges brethren or ſiſters, or contract mariage with any of them, without the eſpeciall licence aſſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; agrement firſt therevnto had and obteined of the kinges highnes in writinge vnder his gracis great ſeale, or defyle or deflour any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge maryed, ſhall be demed and adiuged a traitour to the king and to his realme. And that euery ſuche offence here after to be done made or perpetra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, contrary to this acte, ſhall be adiudged and demed to be highe treaſon.<note place="margin">Treaſon,</note> And that euery man ſo offendinge, and their abettours, procurers, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, counſaylours, and ayders, being laufully conuycte of any ſuche of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence accordinge to the lawes of this realme, ſhal haue and ſuffre ſuch and like peines and execution of death, loſſes of priuileges of ſainctuary and for faytures of landes tenementes and hereditamentes to al intentes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, as in caſes of high treaſon apperteyneth.<note place="margin">Sainctuary.</note> Sauynge to all and euery perſon and perſons, bodies politike and corporate, their heires and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and to the heires and ſucceſſours of euery of them, other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord Thomas Howarde, and his heires, and all other perſons, which ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hereafter to be atteinted by auctoritie of this acte, and their heires and euery of them, all ſuche right, tytle, intereſte, poſſeſſion, leaſes, annuities, rentes, ſeruices, reuercions, remaynders, offices, fees, commons, conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:150869:29"/> &amp; other commodities profites &amp; hereditamentes, in ſuch maner fourme qualitie &amp; condition, as they or any of them haue had, ſhuld or mighte haue had, if this acte had neuer ben had nor made: Any thing in this preſent act to the contrary therof notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶Prouided alway and be it enacted, that in euery ſuche caſe before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the woman after the laſte day of this parlyament ſo offendynge, beinge within the degrees before ſpecified, ſhall incurre like daunger and penaltie as is before limitted, and ſhall ſuffre ſuche lyke dethe and punyſhemente, as is before appoynted to the man offendyng in maner and fourme expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this acte.</p>
            <closer>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>GOD SAVE THE KYNGE.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <head>ARMA · REGIS · ANGLIE · ET · F·</head>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
